<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Foure sermons preached and publikely taught by Richard Leake, preacher of the word of God at Killington, within the baronrie of Kendall, and countie of Westmerland: immediately after the great visitation of the pestilence in the fore-sayd countie.</title>
            <author>Leake, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1599</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 213 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05205</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15342</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106749</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842459</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842459</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7112</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05205)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7112)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 473:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Foure sermons preached and publikely taught by Richard Leake, preacher of the word of God at Killington, within the baronrie of Kendall, and countie of Westmerland: immediately after the great visitation of the pestilence in the fore-sayd countie.</title>
                  <author>Leake, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 116 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Felix Kingston, for Thomas Man,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1599.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Each sermon has caption title.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7112:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7112:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>FOVRE</hi> SERMONS, PREACHED AND PVB<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIKELY TAVGHT BY RICHARD LEAKE, Preacher of the word of God at <hi>Killing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> within the Baronrie of <hi>Kendall,</hi> and Countie of <hi>Weſtmerland:</hi> immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after the great viſitation of the peſtilence in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd Countie.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ezechiel</hi> 24. <hi>verſ.</hi> 13.</bibl>
               <p>Thou remaineſt in thy filthines and wickedneſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I would haue purged thee, and thou waſt not pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged thou ſhalt not bee purged from thy filthines, till I haue cauſed my wrath to fall vpon thee.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON,</hi> Imprinted by FELIX KINGSTON, for <hi>Thomas Man.</hi> 1599.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:7112:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7112:2"/>
            <head>TO THE WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVLL, M. THOMAS STIKELAND, AND M. IAMES BEL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LINGHAM, Eſquires, and two of her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Iuſtices of the peace, within the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronrie of Kendall, and countie of Weſtmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, RICHARD LEAKE wiſheth all graces <hi>needefull for this life, and the continuall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of all graces pertaining to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, to the ende of their dayes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not vnknowne vnto your worſhips, and to vs all round about, what great and manifold dangers haue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſpread all our countrie, by the ſpace of theſe two laſt yeares
<pb facs="tcp:7112:6"/>
and more, as well by dearth, as alſo by ſtrange &amp; fearefull diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, and ſickneſſes. It is no leſſe knowne vnto vs alſo, how little good, and ſmall reliefe, all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward meanes of remedie and comfort brought vnto the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed ones in their extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and who knoweth not how lamentable and wofull was the ſtate of the afflicted one, (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in ſuch places as were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the peſtilence) and what feare came vpon vs all thorough that their affliction; what mourning amongſt them, and daily deuiſes amongſt our ſelues, how to auoide &amp; eſcape dangers? I wiſh from my heart, that the originall breeding, and
<pb facs="tcp:7112:6"/>
firſt occaſion of theſe lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble times, were as well knowne, or herafter may be knowne of vs all, <hi>viz.</hi> how that it was not infection of the ayre, diſtempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature in their bodies, much leſſe the malitious and diueliſh practiſes of witches, or yet blinde fortune, or any other ſuch like imagined cauſes, which were breeders of theſe euils. But the maſſe and multitude of our ſins, in rebelling againſt the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie one of <hi>Jſrael,</hi> theſe (I ſay) haue been the prouokers of the Almightie, to make vs drinke of the cup of afflictions, theſe haue pulled vpon vs al theſe plagues, and brought vpon vs all theſe fearefull and afflicted times,
<pb facs="tcp:7112:3"/>
wherein we haue lately been: which poynt, that it might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare plaine to the ſight &amp; view of all my neighbours (whoſe hearts haue awaked at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding of the ſaid calamities) I haue laboured in this little trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe following, to make knowne, what hath cauſed all theſe woes, and who hath wrought and brought vnto vs better dayes, as alſo what dutie we owe to the Lord, for our gracious and long deſired deliuerance. Which I am bold to dedicate vnto your Worſhips, and that for two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects: firſt, for that I perſwade my ſelfe, that you are both fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable, and alſo forward to entertaine, and bid welcome all
<pb facs="tcp:7112:3"/>
that bring the glad tidings of ſaluation: whereby I am reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that you will not only your ſelues accept and take in good part, theſe my poore labours, but alſo patronize, countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and defend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt al thoſe, who ſhall deride and ſcoffe at them, as they doe at all good things, in my ſelf or others, and ſecondly, for that you be Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and Iuſtices within thoſe limits and precincts, moſt parts whereof haue bin infected moſt pitifully, and (I am perſwaded) moſt iuſtly, for thoſe great and capitall ſinnes, which rule and raigne amongſt vs: as groſſe Poperie, and blinde ſuperſtition in very many places, in ſo much,
<pb facs="tcp:7112:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:7112:4"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:7112:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:7112:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:7112:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:7112:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:7112:8"/>
that I am afraide, that that ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable Idoll of indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Maſſe is vſed in diuerſe places about vs, and that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry boldly: adde hereunto, fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy drunkenneſſe, abhominable whoredomes, open profanation of the Sabbath, vnlawfull pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimes, with infinite many moe, which the further they bee rip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped into, the more filthy ſtinch ariſeth out of them. Theſe and ſuch like ſinnes (I ſay) being ſo pregnant and riſe amongſt vs: I doubt not, but as you eſpied them, and heard them cryed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt by worde and writing, you with the reſt of your aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciats ioyning with you, will holde on in zeale of Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb facs="tcp:7112:8"/>
the peace of Gods children, and the diſcharge of your owne dueties, that theſe ſinnes may haue thoſe lawes executed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, which moſt chriſtianly is prouided in this land, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining them: which (no doubt) ſhall ſo greatly tend to the glorie of God, the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the couſe of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and the flouriſhing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of our chriſtian common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth that in ſhort ſpace, the excellent effects of this zealous gouernement, ſhall proue the trueth and vprightnes thereof. And thus briefely I ceaſe: com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting this little worke, and the iſſue thereof, for acceptance at your Worſhips hands, and
<pb facs="tcp:7112:9"/>
all other that ſhall reade it, to the wiſedome of him, who hath the diſpoſing of the hearts, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of Kings and rulers, euen one God, and three perſons, the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Spirit, to whome be glorie, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, dominion and praiſe for euermore.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your VVorſhips bounden,</hi> Richard Leake.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:7112:9"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He occaſion (good reader) of my offering this poore mite into the Lords treaſurie, and of ſending abroade this fruit, which the increaſe of my ſmall talent bringeth forth vnto the Lords familie, was this: I pleaſed God by the ſpace of two yeares together, to giue our country (in the North parts of this land) a taſte of his power in iudgement, being prouoked there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by our manifold enormious ſinnes: he vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited vs with many and grieuous ſickneſſes, as first with the hot feuer, after, with the bloodie iſſue, and lastly, most fearefully with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame diſeaſe of the pestilence, inflicted vpon many, and ſhaken at all in our whole countrie. And albeit neither I, nor any of the people vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my charge, were infected therewith, yet had we all of vs, the cauſe thereof within our ſinfull hearts, as well as any others: it had inuironed
<pb facs="tcp:7112:10"/>
vs almost round about, we had ſcarcely any way to turne vs, but mourning might be heard; ſo that we expected no better than neighbours fare. Furthermore, in this time, and before (as it is well knowne) the Lord our God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> did cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten and puniſh this whole land with dearth and famine of bread, and ſcarcitie of other victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als in diuers places, ſince which time of tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, it hath pleaſed him (who is God, bleſſed for euer amen) to make knowne his power in mercie, as he had before manifested the ſame in iudgement. For be gaue plentie and cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of bread and all kinde of victuals in ſtead of ſcarcitie and dearth: hee extinguiſhed the heate of ſickeneſſes in thoſe places where it was moſt feruent, &amp; with-held it from thoſe places vnto which it was most fearefully threatned, ſo that then might be heard amongst vs, mirth in ſtead of mourning, ſongs in ſtead of doleful ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; gladſome ſalutations in meetings, in ſtead of diligent ſhunning each of others preſence, for feare of infection. The boistrous ſtormes of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions now driuen away, and calme ſhowers of comfort deſcending: the cloudes of his heauie diſpleaſure now being disperſed, and the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his fauourable countenance ſhining vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs: ſickneſſe now ceaſed and health restored: famine taken away, and plentie ministred; I thought it high time not onely to preach vnto the people of my owne charge, theſe ſermons
<pb facs="tcp:7112:10"/>
following (which teach plainely what vſe we are to make of theſe and ſuch like workes of God, and what dutie they binde vs vnto) but alſo to publiſh them for the benefite of all ſuch as the doctrine doth pertaine vnto. This occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and opportunitie offered (being well conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of all them who ſhall reade theſe Sermons) may ſerue ſufficiently to excuſe me of all ſuch wants as ſhall be espyed in me: for the prouerbe is not more olde than true: a little betime is worth much too late. <hi>How good is a word in due ſeaſon?</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon) Pro. 15.25.</hi> as if he had ſaid, <hi>Oh who is able to declare how good a word is, which commeth in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon?</hi> He himſelfe afterward ſheweth whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it may bee compared: <hi>A worde</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>ſpoken in his place, is like apples of golde, with pictures of ſiluer, Chapter 25. verſe 11.</hi> Now ſure am I, that there is no wiſe bodie can denie, but theſe Sermons were ſpoken in ſeaſon, and alſo publiſhed in ſeaſon, except ſome ſhall ſay, that they had better haue come ſooner, which I could not remedie: and yet I feare not their comming too late: for the dangers are lately paſſed, the deliuerance newly obteyned, the prints or markes of his correcting rods, are yet to be ſeene in many great townes, whoſe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations are as yet ſcarcely repleniſhed: the noyſe of their mournings and gronings, which
<pb facs="tcp:7112:11"/>
were ſore chastened, are as yet ſounding in ſome of our eares: his gracious bleſſings are as yet euen in our mouthes; ſo that neither his puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments vpon the wicked, his chastiſements vpon his children, nor his ſeuerall bleſſings vpon them both, now againe multiplied, can poſſiblie be out of memorie. If any ſay that they (ſuch as they are) be publiſhed ouer hastely, becauſe peraduenture they may ſeeme to preuent the publiſhing of ſome more learned mans worke taken in hand vpon the like occaſion: I anſwer, that euen for this purpoſe I ſtayed theſe my Sermons a whole ſeaſon, gladly deſiring, and earnestly expecting the publiſhing of ſome of their labours, vpon the ſame occaſion, and to the ſame end, that I haue publiſhed theſe: yea, ſo long I ſtayed, till I feared, that if I ſhould haue lingered any longer, the fitnes of the time would haue ſtolen away; and yet could I heare of none which went about or intended any ſuch matter. Wherefore thus long I ſtayed, looking for ſome mans labours to doe more good, and no longer would I deferre, least there ſhould be no mans labours ſet forth vpon the ſame occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which might doe any good.</p>
            <p>Now then (the premiſes conſidered) I pray thee Christian reader, to take in good part, this my labour, and then it ſhall be as an earnest pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of ſome riper fruits out of my poore garden,
<pb facs="tcp:7112:11"/>
when God ſhall minister a fit ſeaſon to gather them, and to ſend them abroode, I ayme at no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing herein, but the glorie of God, the benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of others, and the diſcharge of my owne dutie, if by any meanes I might attaine there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, though but in ſome ſmall meaſure: and though I miſſe thereof with men; yet not with God, who regardeth and accepteth the will and deſire. As for the malitious and enuious car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers and ſcorners, who haue Eagles eyes to ſee motes in godly mens labours, but blinde as Moales, to ſee beames of wickednes in their own liues; readie to cenſure others of all wants, but ſooth themſelues in their owne wayes, if they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie me, it is but their propertie, if raſhlie they cenſure, and iudge amiſſe of me, it is their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, if they with open mouth barke at me, I haue therein many to take part with me, whoſe bookes I ſcantly am worthie to beare after them: none whereof could euer write ſo lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly, deliuer the trueth ſo zealouſly, or doe any worke ſo profitably, but either Atheiſt, Papiſt, ſectarie, one wicked perſon or other, was readie at hand eyther priuily or openly, to labour by power and policie, perſwaſion or threatning to hinder the good ſucceſſe of thoſe their labours. I therefore account all their malitious carping and ſcornefull cenſuring, the fruit which their profane lips do daily bring forth. But vnto ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:7112:12"/>
as feare God and haue need to be increaſed by the mutual helpe of their brethren (I ſay) reade theſe ſermons diligently, &amp; meditate vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ye may ſee the works of god, and the vſe yee ought to make of them, when God hath chaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned you by ſickneſſes or any other way, humble your ſelues before God repent and turne neerer vnto him, and againe when he hath mercie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, and granteth vnto you eaſe &amp; comfort, then beware, ſinne no more leaſt a worſe thing come vnto you, which, that it may be fruitfull, God for Chriſt his ſake grant through the mightie working of his holy ſpirit, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which one God, Father, Sonne and holy Ghoſt, be glory and praie for euer. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the Lord:</hi> Richard Leake.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:7112:12"/>
            <head>THE FIRST SERMON OF THE DVTIE OF OVR deliuerance: drawne out of this portion of the word of God following: <hi>viz.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Ioh. 5. verſ. 14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And after that Ieſus found him in the temple, and ſaid vnto him, Behold, thou art made whole, ſinne no more, leaſt a worſe thing come vnto thee.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words are a ſpeech or kind of exhortation,<note place="margin">The ſumme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole verſe.</note> made by our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, vnto the poore man, whom a little before he had healed, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing vnto him the dutie of his late recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued deliuerance: as alſo by a louing &amp; friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly caueat, forewarning him of the feare and danger of a relapſe into ſinne againe, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer follies. Wherein,<note place="margin">The parts of it.</note> for the better explana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the particulars, we haue to conſider theſe parts or ſpeciall circumſtances.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the time when Chriſt vttered theſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> words,<note place="margin">The time whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> 
               <hi>vz.</hi> a little after he had been healed of his great and grieuous paine, to the end hee might the better remember it: and immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he had talked with the Phariſies Chriſt his enemies, leaſt by perſwaſion they ſhould haue corrupted, or by threatning feared him, not to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:7112:13"/>
giue God his due: drawne out of theſe words of the text: <hi>And after that.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, the place where theſe wordes were vttered by our Sauiour Chriſt,<note place="margin">The place where.</note> 
               <hi>vz.</hi> the temple: <hi>he found him in the temple:</hi> a fit place, that ſuch heauenly and diuine words might take more effect. <hi>Dauid</hi> comming into the temple, alwaies his zeale and earneſt deſire to praiſe God was kindled. And if there bee any ſparke of grace, vſually it will burſt out, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into the temple, the ordinarie place where God is worſhipped.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, the wordes of exhortation them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in theſe words:<note place="margin">The words of exhortation themſelues.</note> 
               <hi>and ſaid vnto him, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, thou art made whole, ſinne no more:</hi> a <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> friendly and louing caueat,<note place="margin">The louing caueat.</note> forewarning the daunger of not doing the dutie aforeſaid, in theſe wordes: <hi>leaſt a worſe thing come vnto thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of all theſe parts, and their ſeuerall branches in order.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Of the firſt part. The time whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe words were vttered,<note place="margin">The time whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> was a little after our Sauiour Chriſt had ſhewed the great miracle vpon him, in healing him of his diſeaſe, which had vexed him thirtie eight yeres, to the intent he might the better remember it. Where firſt wee are to note,<note place="margin">Chriſt a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſhepheard.</note> the carefull dealing of Chriſt as a true ſhepheard, to vſe all meanes for ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering into the folde, the loſt and ſtraying
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:7112:13"/>
ſheepe; he omitteth no occaſion, neglecteth no meanes, neither is hindred by any labour, to inſtruct and edifie either by doctrine, or miracle. The like courſe muſt be imitated of all the faithfull ſhepheards of Chriſt Ieſus: <hi>to be inſtant in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.13. <hi>and</hi> 9. <hi>ver.</hi> 21, 22, 23</note> 
               <hi>to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort, to improue, rebuke:</hi> And with <hi>Paul,</hi> to <hi>become all vnto all,</hi> to the ende they <hi>may win ſome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, we note here the dutie of all Gods children, when God hath beſtowed his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings vpon them, euen immediatly thereupon <hi>to render thankes, &amp; ſing praiſes to the higheſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exo.</hi> 15.2, 3. <hi>&amp;c Iudg.</hi> 5.2, 3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Thus did <hi>Moſes</hi> after the great deliuerances God gaue vnto Iſrael. Thus did <hi>Deborah</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God had giuen her victorie ouer her cruell e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie <hi>Siſera.</hi> Thus did <hi>Dauid</hi> for euery mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous bleſſing God ſhewed vpon him, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing this or the like ſpeech:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.12.13.</note> 
               <hi>What ſhall I giue vnto the Lord for all the benefits he hath done vnto me?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.16.</note> And finally thus did the tenth lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per when Chriſt had cleanſed him, returne with ſpeede to giue God praiſe. So that hence I conclude this doctrine,<note place="margin">Delay not thy thankfulnes when God of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth his mercie.</note> that immediatly vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the beſtowing of Gods bleſſings vpon vs, wee ought with thankſgiuing to put them in remembrance. As moſt of vs now liuing in the North parts of this land, haue moſt largely taſted the comfortable, and neuer ſtinting ſtreame of his mercies. Firſt, in preſeruing vs
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:7112:14"/>
in the pinching time of dearth. Next,<note place="margin">Some particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars wherein the North-parts haue found God lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to them.</note> in tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our pouertie into plentie. Thirdly, his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous ſauing vs in the vehement &amp; ouer-ſpreading time of the peſtilence. So that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to mans expectation we haue been within the reach of it: yet euen then hath his power in mercie ouerreached and preuented the ſame. So that in regard of theſe late receiued deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances,<note place="margin">Our danger by-paſt.</note> I may very fitly vſe the patheticall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion that <hi>Dauid</hi> vſeth, after a large ſuruey of his mercies:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 105.</note> 
               <hi>O that men would therefore praiſe the Lord for his goodneſſe, and declare the wonders that hee doth for the children of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Againe, the time when our Sauiour Chriſt vttered theſe words, was immediatly after the man healed, had talked with the Phariſies, Chriſt his vtter enemies:<note place="margin">The ſubtill dealing of the Phariſies.</note> the Phariſies dealt with him as they vvere accuſtomed to deale with all others, who they ſaw to fauour Chriſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> either for his doctrine or his miracles. Firſt to trie if they could perſwade them, that Chriſt was a ſeducer,<note place="margin">Note. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9.24. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.47.48.</note> and that they runne into great danger if any way they did affect him. Thus dealt they with the man that was borne blind, whom Chriſt had healed,<note place="margin">The crueltie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, when the other would not preuaile. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9.22.</note> and with thoſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> they ſent to attach Chriſt. But if by this perſwaſion they could not preuaile, then they aſſaied a ſharper courſe, euen to threate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them vvith the law, and to caſt them out of their Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagouges:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:7112:14"/>
by which two meanes they held backe many, yea euen of the chiefer ſort,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12.42, 43.</note> that they durſt not openly profeſſe any good will to Chriſt. Our Sauiour Chriſt therefore eſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the danger this poore man was in, after he had talked with the Phariſies,<note place="margin">The loue and care of Chriſt to call vpon vs when we are in moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</note> thought it then a fit time, euen immediatly thereupon, to vtter theſe words of the text, thereby to bring into his remembrance afreſh his late receiued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit: as alſo to make him bold and zealous in the courſe of a Chriſtian, by ſhewing him the danger that would enſue, if he did it not.</p>
            <p>Here may we note,<note place="margin">Dangerous for weak ones to be conuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before perſecutors.</note> that it is very dangerous for weake Chriſtians to hearken to the ſubtill perſwaſions of Gods enemies: or to be called before them being in authoritie and to bee threatned: as may appeare by the ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reuolts and recantations of many weake Chriſtians in the Primitiue Church, &amp; our owne Church of England, when they were vrged thereunto by perſecuting tyrants, or bloodſucking By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops.<note place="margin">A ſpeciall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie againſt feare and fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in our troubles for the Goſpell ſake.</note> Therfore that neither the one may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them, nor the other terrifie them, they are themſelues to vſe inceſſant prayer, that God would giue them his ſpirit, to leade them into all trueth: and being in the trueth, that he would in his mercie vouchſafe them the ſpirit of boldnes, <hi>to profeſſe his name euen before kings and princes, and neuer be aſhamed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:7112:15"/>
               <note place="margin">The dutie of good paſtors.</note>Secondly in Chriſt we are here to note the dutie of good ſhepheards ouer their flockes, as alſo of ſtronger Chriſtians to their weaker and new conuerted brethren,<note place="margin">The dutie of one Chriſtian to another.</note> 
               <hi>vz.</hi> where they eſpie the intrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of Satan ſo buſie, both by perſwaſions and threatnings, <hi>to quench the ſpirit of God</hi> in new conuerts,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.19. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 22.</note> euen then to bee as readie as Chriſt was here, whenſoeuer they meete with them,<note place="margin">Exhort one another daily. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 2.3, 4.</note> either in publike exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or priuate conferences, with Chriſt to put them in minde of their late deliuerances out of the clawes of Satan, <hi>and kingdome of darknes,</hi> &amp; of the danger y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> will enſue, if euer they fall away. And thus much for the firſt part of the text, drawne out of theſe wordes, <hi>and after that.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond part.</note>The ſecond part, <hi>vz.</hi> The place where. The place where our maſter Chriſt vttered theſe wordes to the man whom hee had hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led before, was the temple. Ieſus after the miracle ſhewed in healing the man, got him out of the way for a certaine ſpace: and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into the temple, there he found the man vpon whom the miracle of healing had been ſhewed, lately come from talking with the Phariſies: whereupon Chriſt, what in regarde of the vrgent occaſion, and what in regard of the fitnes of the place, vttereth the words of exhortation in my text: <hi>Behold, thou art made
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:7112:15"/>
whole.</hi> The temple was the place where God had promiſed his preſence, when they came either to pray, or to perſwade vnto Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie: as the Lord promiſed vnto <hi>Salomon</hi> the builder of the temple in theſe words: <hi>And the Lord ſaid vnto him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 9.3.</note> 
               <hi>I haue heard thy prayer and thy ſupplication that thou haſt made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me. I haue hallowed this houſe (which thou haſt built) to put my name there for euer: and mine eyes, and mine heart ſhall be there perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually.</hi> Chriſt therefore in this temple perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto newnes of life, had the promiſe of his fathers preſence, to make his perſwaſion powerful, as alſo to print in the hart of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, a more reuerend regarde and eſtimation thereof being deliuered.<note place="margin">Dauid a type of the militant Church. Reade <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84. <hi>&amp; Pſa.</hi> 122.1.2 1. <hi>Chon.</hi> 29.9.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> being a true type and figure of the Militant Church here on earth, neuer came into the temple but his heart leapt for ioy, his ioy was increaſed, and his zeale kindled: yea that which being out of the temple he could neuer attaine vnto, was in the temple made partaker of.<note place="margin">Salomons temple a type of the ſpiritual temple.</note> Though that temple was a type and figure of the ſpirituall temple neuer made with hands: and there is not the ſame vſe of it now, as there was then, yet haue wee at this day two things,<note place="margin">Two things now reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s temple. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.24.</note> that may fitly reſemble that temple, and where God wil as well heare the praiers, and receiue the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of his Church, being done in ſpirit and trueth, as he would then.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:7112:16"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is the godly ſocieties and aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of the righteous,<note place="margin">Godly ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties meete to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting one another. <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.20.</note> whereſoeuer and when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they meete together, according to the rule and warrant of Gods worde: to ſuch Chriſt hath promiſed his preſence, ſaying: <hi>Where two or three are gathered together in my name, there am I in the middeſt of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond is our ordinary aſſemblies and meetings together at the houſe of prayer,<note place="margin">Publike aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of the faithfull at the houſe of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</note> to powre forth prayers to the Lord, be partakers of the word preached, and adminiſtration of the Sacraments. Where ſuch aſſemblies are employed to theſe aforeſaid vſes, they are not as the Prophet calleth the temple in his time, <hi>the den of theeues:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 56.7. <hi>Ierem.</hi> 7.11. <hi>Mar.</hi> 11.17.</note> but <hi>they are euen the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed throne &amp; kingdome of Chriſt Ieſus, to whoſe faith and conſtancie Chriſt hath promiſed ſuch power, that euen the gates of hell ſhall neuer bee able to preuaile againſt them.</hi> In theſe two temples (as I may call them) when we meete with our brethren, it is not our duties to prate and chat of worldly matters, but rather euery one of vs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.13.</note> 
               <hi>to exhort one another while it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to day, leaſt we be hardened through the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulnes of ſinne.</hi> Yea, <hi>to keepe the profeſſion of our hope without wauering, and to prouoke one another vnto loue and to good workes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.23, 24, 25.</note> 
               <hi>not forſaking the godly fellowſhip that ought to bee amongst Gods children.</hi> And to be carefull al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to cheriſh and embolden the weake,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:7112:16"/>
putting them in mind of their miraculous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance out of the kingdome of darknes, into the kingdome and cleere light of the Goſpell. And thus much of the ſecond part.</p>
            <p>Of the third part, which is the words of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation themſelues: wherein wee haue to conſider theſe three branches following.</p>
            <p>Firſt, a rehearſall of the benefit done to the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> man: <hi>behold thou art made whole.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The principall cauſe of his long ſickneſſe,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> from which Chriſt had now deliuered him, was his ſinnes and iniquities, which I gather out of theſe words: <hi>Sinne no more.</hi> As if hee ſhould ſay, ſinne hath bin the cauſe of thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſickneſſe: if therefore hereafter thou wilt remaine a ſound man, ſinne no more.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, what muſt be the effect of this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> by Chriſt, or the dutie of his deliuerance, which is the ſubiect of this treatiſe, euen true repentance, ſet downe here by the former part of true repentance: which is, to <hi>ſinne no more,</hi> or to ceaſe from ſin.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>The bountifulnes of God ought to leade vs to repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the firſt branch: <hi>Behold, thou art made whole.</hi> Where firſt we are to conſider that our Sauiour vſeth a word of attention, or to make the matter hee hath in hand take more effect, ſaith: <hi>Ecce,</hi> Behold.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32. <hi>v.</hi> 5.7.</note> The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of any extraordinary matter, alwaies v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth an hebrew verbe, importing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like, which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:7112:17"/>
is <hi>Selah:</hi> ſo likewiſe the ſeruant of God <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> vſing any veheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t exhortation, common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hath this word, behold or reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, as thus: <hi>Behold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.19. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.</note> 
               <hi>I ſet before thee this day, life and death, bleſſing and curſing.</hi> The Prophets of the Lord ſpeaking either of the manifeſtation of Chriſt in his humane nature, or of his ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming againe to iudgement, or of any ſuch great matter, vſeth this word <hi>behold.</hi> As <hi>Eſay: Tell the daughter Sion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 62.11. <hi>Zach.</hi> 9.9. <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.5. <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>Behold, thy King com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, meekely riding on an aſſe, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lachie: Behold, the day co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth that ſhall burne like an ouen, and all the proud, yea and all that doe wickedly ſhall bee ſtubble.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apoc.</hi> 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>Behold, be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth with clowdes, and euery eye ſhall ſee him, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>and</hi> 22.7.</note> 
               <hi>Behold I come ſhortly.</hi> Euen ſo here as a preface to the declaration of the benefit done to him, Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Behold:</hi> giue eare, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der well what I haue done for thee, paſſe not lightly ouer that miracle I haue ſhewed vpon thee, in giuing thee health. Where we are to note,<note place="margin">Receiue his word, miracles and mercies with attentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> that GOD would haue vs receiue his word, his exhortations, threatnings, bleſſings and miracles, with attention, heede taking, and waying well, who it is that doth ſuch things for vs, and what is done, as we ourſelues.</p>
            <p>O my countrimen, and deare brethren in Chriſt Ieſus, (for whoſe ſake the Lorde hath moued me to penne this little treatiſe) haue iuſt occaſion to giue eare what the Lords Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7112:17"/>
ſoundeth in our eares daily,<note place="margin">Aboue many others the North parts.</note> after our great and late receiued deliuerances: euen thus, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thou art made whole, &amp;c.</hi> VVhereunto let euery one of vs fill our families, our meetings, and conferences with this heauenly harmonie and ſweete ſounding melodie, anſwering the former <hi>behold,</hi> ſaying then, ſith it is ſo indeede: <hi>My ſoule praiſe thou the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 13.1.2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 57.7.8.</note> 
               <hi>and all that is within me praiſe his holy name. Awake thou my glorie, awake lute and harpe, I my ſelfe will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake right early.</hi> And let vs one prouoke an other to praiſe the Lord of might, for his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous mercies, as <hi>Deborah</hi> ſtirred vp her owne ſoule, and <hi>Barake,</hi> to ſing praiſe to God for their triumphant victories: <hi>Vp Deborah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5.12. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>vp, ariſe ſing a ſong: ariſe Barak, &amp;c.</hi> Euen ſo, vp O Weſtmerland, Comberland, and Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thumberland: vp ye ſeuerall townes, congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations and families, &amp; euery particular ſoule; whoſe ſafetie the liuing Lord, by the ſhadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wings of his mercie hath preſerued, and ſing a ſong: ceaſe not, but make the earth ſound againe with the voyce of thanſgiuing, and prouoking one another with ſuch pathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall ſpeeches as this: <hi>O behold how greatly the Lord hath loued vs, how mightily he hath deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, and hath ſhadowed vs vnder the wings of his mercie, vntill the dangers were ouer paſt.</hi> And thus much for this word <hi>behold.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the benefit it ſelfe. In the manifeſtation
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:7112:18"/>
of the benefit, wee haue to conſider foure cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, what his ſicknes was. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> how long he had been infected there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, what meanes he vſed himſelfe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> for his recouerie, and yet found none. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by what meanes at length hee was made whole.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The firſt cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance.</note>Of the firſt circumſtance. Although it can not be gathered by expreſſe words in the text what manner of diſeaſe it was that troubled him:<note place="margin">Not expreſly, but by circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</note> yet by circumſtances it may probably be coniectured. In the 3. verſe of this chapter is ſet downe, that blinde, lame, and withered reſorted to the poole, waiting for the mouing of the water: ſo that it is very likely, that one of theſe he was. To ſet downe which he was, I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that a certaine lamenes or witherednes did occupie &amp; poſſeſſe his whole body, which is proued by his anſwer to Chriſt, verſ. 7. Sir, I haue no man whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the water is troubled to put me into the poole. And the Greeke word ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth, to be caried by the helpe of another.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond circumſtance.</note>Of the ſecond circumſtance. The text ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth downe that hee had beene diſeaſed 38. yeres, verſ. 5. a long time, and if a man ſhould conſider of it with mortall eye, it were able to make him thinke God either had forgotten him,<note place="margin">Though long we languiſh, yet ſtill waite with patience.</note> or giuen him ouer. Yet hence if we right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weigh it, we may conſider many excellent poynts. Firſt, we are here inſtructed to pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:7112:18"/>
for the time of thirtie eight yeeres was very long,<note place="margin">Caluin. in Ioh. cap. <hi>5.</hi> ver. <hi>7.</hi> quantumuis diù nos ſuſpenſos teneat, ſic anxiè gemamus ſub noſtris arumnis, vt longi tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris taedium nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam nos exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimet.</note> wherein God deferred his helping hand in healing this miſerable man: which notwithſtanding God had decreed from the beginning to doe. The like patience ought Gods children to haue in bearing any other afflictions of the body whatſoeuer: for as hee dealt here with this poore ſoule, ſo dealeth he for the moſt part with his whole Church, and euery particular member of the ſame. He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred the deliuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his people Iſrael,<note place="margin">Exod. chap. <hi>1.</hi> to chap. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> from vnder the captiuitie and bondage of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> euen for the ſpace of foure hundred and odde yeeres, yea ſo long, till the enemies thought to haue them their bondſlaues for euer, and his poore Church deſpaired of their deliuerance.<note place="margin">Reade 1. <hi>Sam. chap.</hi> 17. <hi>to chap.</hi> 31. where is ſet downe the death of Saul.</note> He ſuffered <hi>Dauid</hi> (after hee was annoynted king ouer Iſrael) to be for many yeeres toſſed to and fro as an abiect, and at euery turne to bee in danger, yea euen forſaken and hated of all, like a forlorne creature: ſo that <hi>Dauid</hi> (if he had not poſſeſſed his ſoule with patience, and relied on the promiſes of the Lord) might haue thought Gods mercies turned into meere mockerie, and his promiſe no better then a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing puffe of winde.<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 38.</note> He ſuffered his rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Iſrael to lie ſo long weather beaten vnder the captiuitie of the Babylonians, that though there was exta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t a promiſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his own mouth, <hi>that a remnant ſhould returne:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 14.22. <hi>&amp;</hi> 39.25.</note> yet were they
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:7112:19"/>
out of al hope euer to returne, but euen in that ſtrange land to lie buried in the duſt &amp; aſhes of euerlaſting ignominie &amp; reproch. Yea ſo hopeleſſe were they of any returne, that the Lord God was enforced to ſend his Prophet vnto them, and to demonſtrate their deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,<note place="margin">Ezek. <hi>32.</hi> ver. <hi>1.</hi> to verſ. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> (though now in their iudgement deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate) by the ſimilitude of giuing life to a great number of dead mens bones diſperſed and ſcattered here and there.</p>
            <p>To conclude and come nier our own times: the Lord ſuffered for many hundred yeeres this land of ours, wherein we liue, to lie fallow and ouergrowne altogether firſt with Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme, and then with the brambles and buſhes of Poperie and ſuperſtition, ſmall hope that euer it ſhould haue bin a well tilled field, and ſweete garden to the Lorde. Many the like proofes might I bring, yea euen from the head of the Church Chriſt himſelfe: but the former alreadie alleadged, are ſufficient to proue my propounded propoſition, <hi>vz.</hi> that as Chriſt deferred for the ſpace of thirtie eight yeeres to cure this lame man, the like he hath done, and doth now, in afflicting his Church generally, or any particular member thereof, be it of the body or the ſoule.</p>
            <p>Now followeth the ſecond branch of my propoſition: which is, that for all this long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay of the Lord, yet was it decreed with him
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:7112:19"/>
from the beginning <hi>in the fulnes of time,</hi> and his owne appointed ſeaſon, to worke their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerances. So when the foure hundred and thirtie yeres were expired, the length and date of time, hee had decreed the Iſraelites ſhould be in captiuitie and bondage vnder <hi>Pharaoh:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.41.</note> euen the very ſame day did the Lord bring his people Iſrael out of Egypt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.4.</note> euen with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpoyle of their enemies, and the enriching of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. So did he with his ſeruant <hi>Dauid,</hi> when hee had a long time ſoked him in afflictions, and fined him in the furnace of aduerſitie, ſo that thereby he had fitted him for ſuch a future dignitie: euen then did the Lorde take <hi>Saul</hi> out of the way,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.</note> and with great pompe crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Dauid</hi> King of Iſrael.</p>
            <p>The like may be ſaid of the captiuitie of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah and Ieruſalem vnder the Babylonians: who when they thought they ſhould neuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the temple any more, to build vp the breaches thereof, and to ſing praiſes to <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uah</hi> in their owne land: yet then, when they leaſt looked for it, did the Lord bring them againe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 1, 2, 3, 4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> and gaue them power to repayre the breaches of the temple, and to build vp the broken walles of Ieruſalem. And withall, thoſe roddes of his indignation (I meane the Babylonians) hee caſt into the fire, and vtterly conſumed, with the breath of his noſthrils. And how true finde we this by the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:7112:20"/>
experience of our owne nation, that when the Goſpell and the light thereof was euen as it were quite buried, Gods glorie defaced, his Saints (if any were raiſed vp) cruelly murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and in ſtead therof, firſt the ſtinking dung of Paganiſme, and after that the perilous poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of poperie planted, ſmall hope that euer any redreſſe ſhould be had: yet euen then did the Lord put into the heart of King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. of famous memorie, to begin a refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, King <hi>Edward</hi> the 6. painefully to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the ſame, and now our gratious <hi>Debo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah</hi> to finiſh and build vp that which the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two in their owne did not: whoſe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and gratious gouernment God long proſper, with encreaſe of knowledge, zeale and power, for the glorie of his great name, the propagation of the crowne and kingdom of Chriſt Ieſus, and the vtter defacing and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing out of the traces of Antichriſt. <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to conclude by the example of this poore man, he had been diſeaſed 38. yeeres, old, and ſo the leſſe hope, withered and dried vp, ſo as to the iudgement of all he was like to die ſo, as long he had liued. Yet when Chriſt ſaw his appoynted and due time, he came and made him a ſound man as euer he was. Hence (as I ſaid before) let vs learne patience in our greateſt miſeries: and though our burthens
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:7112:20"/>
which the Lord hath laid vpon vs bee ſuch, as oft they make vs groane, yet ſtill let vs ſigh and groane vnder hope,<note place="margin">The burthens of the faithfull vpholden by the Lord.</note> with full aſſurance groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon Gods promiſe, that when he ſeeth it moſt meete, hee will worke our deliuerance. Let the due conſideration hereof, take away from vs all murmurings, grudgings, or male-contented hearts in all our troubles, whether they bee troubles of the body, or anguiſhes of the minde, ſtill grounding our patience vpon Gods reuealed promiſe in his word, as thus: <hi>All things ſhall fall out for the beſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 38. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13.</note> 
               <hi>to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that loue God. Nothing ſhall ſeparate vs from the loue of God in Chriſt.</hi> And, <hi>God is faithfull, who hath promiſed he will lay no more vpon his children, then he will make them able to beare: but in the middeſt of the temptation he will giue them a happie iſſue and ioyfull deliuerance.</hi> And when thou art wearie therewith, haue recourſe vnto Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.28.</note> and he will take thy burthen vpon his backe, and relieue thee.</p>
            <p>Now, if any demaund of me the reaſon why the Lord doth ſo ſore, and for ſo long a ſpace afflict his children before hee worke their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance: my anſwere is this. The Lord doth it for diuers ends: ſome whereof I haue here (for the comfort of his afflicted ones) ſet down as followeth.</p>
            <p>Firſt the Lord doth ſore afflict his people,<note place="margin">1 Reaſons al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged, why God doth ſo long &amp; largely afflict his own people.</note> and long delay before he worke their deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:7112:21"/>
to teach them humilitie, leaſt they ſhuld out of meaſure be puffed vp. For this cauſe did he ſore afflict and buffet the Apoſtle <hi>Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, to teach them obedience, leaſt they ſhould be too ſtiffe-necked: thus did he tame the Iſraelites.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, to make them more carefully learne his law, and continually ſtudie therein. Thus dealt the Lord with <hi>Dauid,</hi> in afflicting him ſo long, til <hi>Dauid</hi> could ſay from his very hart, <hi>It is good for me that I haue been afflicted, that I might learne thy law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, he afflicteth them, leaſt they erre and goe aſtray in the dark deſert of this world: for this end alſo did <hi>Dauid</hi> make of his afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſaying: <hi>Before I was afflicted I went wrong.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fiftly, to make vs become obedient ſpouſes vnto our husband Chriſt Ieſus, that in matters for Gods glorie, and our ſaluation, wee admit of none elſe, neither in part or whole, for the foundation and cornerſtone of our ſaluation. Thus afflicted hee Iudah and Ieruſalem, who were wont to play the harlots vnder euerie greene tree.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Laſtly, hee continueth his afflictions vpon vs, to teach vs that our ſinnes are the cauſe of all our ſorrow, and therefore to ſinne no more, leaſt a worſe thing come vnto vs. Thus afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hee for a long time this poore man, whom he now had healed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:7112:21"/>The Lord grant for his infinit mercies ſake,<note place="margin">The applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> that the long and late afflictions laid vpon vs and our countrie, may worke theſe aforeſayd effects in vs, euen to pull downe our proude hearts, to mollifie our hard hearts, to inſtruct and teach our ignorant hearts, to direct aright our vnſtable and wandring hearts, to make chaſt and pure our vnchaſt and whoriſh harts, and to redreſſe and amend our wicked and tranſgreſſing hearts: that ſo our pride being turned into humilitie, ſtiffeneckednes into cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, inſtabilitie into certaintie, diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie againſt our husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Chriſt, into loyaltie of a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience vnſpotted: and to conclude, our daily ſinning into a continual godly ſorowing for the ſame: we may then ſay with <hi>Dauid,</hi> (as many I meane as haue theſe aforeſaid effects wrought in them by their afflictions) glad are wee, and good hath it been for vs, that long, largely, and yet moſt louingly, the Lord hath afflicted vs, ſeeing they haue taught vs the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie of our daies, the danger of our ſinnes, the loathing of this wretched world, and a loue of the life to come.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> In this courſe of continued afflictions vpon the Church of God, note euery profitable and neceſſary doctrine, <hi>vz.</hi> It is the vſuall manner of dealing with the Lord, to defer his helping hand and full deliuerance, till all meanes of helpe inuented by man bee fruſtrate, and the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:7112:22"/>
caſe in the iudgement of many ſeemeth deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate:<note place="margin">God helpeth when all other meanes are helples. The end of the Lord ſo long deferring.</note> thus did he with this poore man, and in all the aforenamed proofes. And he doth it for this eſpeciall end, that in victories, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, or deliuerances, God might haue his owne, which is euen the whole glorie. If wee had no warrant out of Gods word, for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of this poynt: yet our owne expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience theſe two yeeres by-paſt,<note place="margin">Our countries late viſitation approue it.</note> in the moſt places of our countrie, is of ſufficiencie to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie and witnes how true a doctrine his is, ſeeing that no watching, no gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, great multitudes or carefull keeping could preuent his puniſhments, but they came vpon vs: no phiſick could ſtint it, but it encreaſed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued: yea when all mans remedies were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred, yet were the poore afflicted ones ſtill remedileſſe: ſo that great townes, many congregations, and infinit families eſpying all theſe hopes, now hopeleſſe: and though by ſome called comforts, yet comfortles now, haue in vtter deſpayre of them all, let goe the anchor, pulled downe the ſayle, and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the whole cuſtodie of their poore toſſed ſhip to him, who firſt raiſed vp the tempeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, and he, euen that mightie God <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uah,</hi> (who iuſtly for our countries rebellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his almightie maieſtie, did wound the hairie ſcalpe of his enemies, and the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of his rebellious Iſrael) did in the end (O
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:7112:22"/>
admire his mercies) heale that which before he had wounded, ſaued vs, that in the ſight and iudgement of many ſeemed as forlorne: and in ſtead of many blacke and gloomy dayes, tokens of his anger, hath at laſt ſpoken peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably vnto vs againe, and granted vs more then we expected, or our harts could deſire. O my countrimen deare, then le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4+ letters">
                  <desc>••••…</desc>
               </gap>rge the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theticall exhortation that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth in his Pſalme, to all men in his t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>red out of dangers: <hi>O that we would therefore praiſe the Lord for his goodneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.5.</note> 
               <hi>and declare abroad the workes that he doth for vs moſt ſinfull men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further, in that he healed this man, which had been poſſeſſed with a lamenes or numnes ſo long a ſpace as thirtie eight yeeres in his whole body, appeareth the exceeding great power of almightie God: for in that the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe was vniuerſall ouer the whole body, and beſides had continued ſo long till he was old,<note place="margin">The power of the Lord ſet forth.</note> there is no rule in phiſicke that euer could giue him any hope of recouerie: yet herein note the vnſpeakable power of the Lorde, that by ſpeaking a word or two, he healed him per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly: in mans hope paſt healing. By the like power hee healed the woman of the bloodie iſſue,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.42.</note> who had ſpent all her ſubſtance vpon Phiſitions, and could not be healed. By this power he healed the woman who had a ſpirit of infirmitie eighteene yeres, and was bowed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:7112:23"/>
together.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 11.43, 44. <hi>Mar.</hi> 7.32. <hi>and</hi> 9.26. <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24.36. <hi>Mar.</hi> 1.42. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6. <hi>Matth.</hi> 14.19.</note> By this power hee raiſed <hi>Lazarus</hi> from death to life, who had lien in his graue foure daies. By this power he made the deaffe to heare, the dumbe to ſpeake, the lame to go, and clenſed the leper. By this power hee fed fiue thouſand with fiue barly loaues and two fiſhes. I may in like ſort ſpeake of this migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and exceeding great power towards all thoſe that are tranſlated and deliuered out of the kingdome of darkneſſe and Satan, into the kingdome and cleere light of the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt. What a great power of the Lord was it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 9.1.20.</note> that perſecuting <hi>Saul</hi> was healed of his ſinne, &amp; made zealous <hi>Paul,</hi> preaching Chriſt Ieſus and him crucified? What a great power was it, that <hi>Mary Magdalene,</hi> in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> raigned &amp; dwelled 7.<note place="margin">The true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of a ſinner mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſteth Gods power. <hi>Luk.</hi> 7.37.38. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> diuels was clea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed, made whole, and a woman euer after to weepe for her ſins, and to waſh Chriſt his feet with her teares? But greater was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> manifeſtation of his power, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he healed the man which had a legion of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels in him. And at this day may euery true conuert ſay: oh the exceeding greatnes of Gods power towards me poore wretch, who being vnder the bondage of ſinne, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the bondſlaue of Satan, all the power that was in me, or that I was able to make, could neuer make me free from that thraldome, till that the exceeding power of GOD, by the ſounding miniſterie of his word, cryed vnto
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:7112:23"/>
me: <hi>Awake thou that ſleepeſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.14.</note> 
               <hi>and ſtand vp from the dead, and Chriſt ſhall giue thee light.</hi> Such a miraculous power, and a powerfull miracle is the raiſing vp of a ſinner from his ſnorting in iniquitie, to walke and runne the race of a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>Moreouer,<note place="margin">Note his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</note> as we note his power in healing him of ſuch a long continuing ſickneſſe: ſo note wee his compaſſionate mercie, in hauing a feeling and before touched with our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties <hi>We haue an high Prieſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.15.</note> 
               <hi>who cannot be tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with the feeling of our infirmities, but was in all things tempted in like ſort as we are, ſinne only excepted.</hi> This his compaſſion and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, made him to weepe ouer Ieruſalem,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.41.</note> view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their great ſins, and his fathers wrath rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to fall vpon them for the ſame. It made him pitie the great multitude of people that came preſſing vpon him, when hee ſaw them as ſheepe without a ſhepheard. It made him to ſigh and groane at the hardnes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples hearts: yea ſo forcible and plentifull was it in him, that hee neuer denyed helpe to the miſerable, comfort to the comfortleſſe, nor heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly counſell to them that carefully ſought for it. His loue to vs for our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is as large as the Eaſt is from the Weſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.12.13.</note> and the North from the South, as great and greater then the loue the father hath to his ſonne, or the mother to the babe ſucking her breaſts: for that hee
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:7112:24"/>
euen ſpreadeth out both his armes of mercie, readie to embrace euery ſinner, truly turning vnto him: and clocketh vs vnto him by his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall mercies,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.37. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.11, 12, 13.</note> euen as the hen gathereth her chickens vnder her wings. Yea, this one thing doth greatly extoll the largenes of his loue and fauour, in that he extendeth it to vs, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any of our merits or deſerts. <hi>For he loued his owne, before euer the foundation of the world was laid:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.23.</note> 
               <hi>ere euer Iacob had done good or euill, he loued him, and hated Eſau.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.12.</note> 
               <hi>He that is Lord ouer all, is rich vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all that call vpon him.</hi> Rich he is in power, able to helpe; rich he is in mercie, moſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and readie to heare all thoſe that call on him faithfully. I ſhould be endleſſe, if I ſhould repeate the proofes of this great loue &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of God,<note place="margin">The loue of God to vs in his ſon Chriſt is endleſſe.</note> in and by his Sonne Chriſt Ieſus. But becauſe his loue to vs is endleſſe, I wil here end the ſpeaking of it with that admiration, wherewith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> endeth his ſpeech of Gods election and reprobation: <hi>O the deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the riches, both of the power and mercies of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.33.</note> 
               <hi>how infinit is the one and the other, not able ſufficiently to be expreſſed by the tongue or penne of any man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Our dutie hence.</note>Our dutie hence that we muſt learne, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation and true repentance: otherwiſe wee ſhall treaſure and hoord vp wrath and clowdes of witneſſes againſt the day of wrath,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:7112:24"/>
and declaration of the iuſt iudgement of God:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.3.4.</note> 
               <hi>Seeing the bountifulnes of God ought to leade vs to repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The comfort we may hence reape is great:<note place="margin">The comfort</note> Art thou ſicke? art thou afflicted? art thou preſſed downe with the ſight of thy ſinnes? crieſt thou after Chriſt, and deſireſt with blind <hi>Bartimeus,</hi> to be healed of thy infirmitie?<note place="margin">No ſore to the Chriſtian but Chriſt will ſerue it.</note> then continue thy crying, labour that thy ſighs and groanes may be increaſed, yea (if it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible) euen to pearce into the heauens. And though thou findeſt not preſent remedie, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre not; conſider Gods power is able to raiſe thee vp when thou art fallen; conſider alſo his mercie to bee ſuch, that although the wife play the harlot, and her husband giue her a bill of diuorcement, hee will neuer receiue her againe: yet ſaith our gratious and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full God vnto our ſick ſoules, turne again thou diſobedient man, whoſoeuer thou bee, and though thou haſt committed whoredom with thy louers,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierem.</hi> 3.2, 3, 4.</note> yet will I receiue thee into my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour againe. And thus much for the ſecond circumſtance to bee conſidered in healing of the man, <hi>vz.</hi> how long hee had beene grieued with his ſicknes.</p>
            <p>Of the third circumſtance, <hi>vz.</hi> what meanes the poore man vſed for his recouerie himſelfe, and yet all in vaine. Here wee muſt conſider, that there was in Ieruſalem a poole or pond
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:7112:25"/>
at the South ſide of the citie,<note place="margin">Tremelius and Iunius in Ioh. <hi>5.</hi> Hebr. Syr.</note> neere vnto the Sheep-market, the name whereof was <hi>Betheſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> or in the Syrian la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guage <hi>Bethcheſda,</hi> which ſignifieth the houſe of bountifulneſſe: for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in that place God moſt mercifully ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed his power, in healing many of their infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities. <hi>Hierom</hi> greatly erreth in calling it <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theder,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gregis domus.</note> which ſignifieth the houſe for beaſts &amp; cattel: for mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is made here of a po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, which was neere vnto the Sheep-market. <hi>Caluine</hi> affirmeth thoſe to want all reaſon,<note place="margin">Cal. in Ioh. c. <hi>5.</hi> ver. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> who call it <hi>Bethſeda,</hi> as though it were a place of fiſhing, adiudging the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to determine of the word more probably, who doe expound it <hi>locus effuſionis,</hi> the place of powring out water. The Hebrew worde ſignifieth a falling downward: for I thinke the water was drawne from it by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duites, that the prieſts might draw the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The vertue of the poole was this, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies at a certaine ſeaſon an Angell deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into it and troubled the water, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer then firſt after the mouing of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtepped in, was made whole of whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer diſeaſe he had.</p>
            <p>Here by the way wee may not thinke, that the vertue of healing conſiſted in the water: for ſaith <hi>Caluine:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cal. ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Sic externum ſymbolum co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendat, vt ſymboli aspectu, ad ipſum vnicum gratiae authorem aegrotire ſpicere cogantur:</hi> For this cauſe doth hee commend the outwarde
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:7112:25"/>
ſigne, that by the ſight thereof, all ſicke men may bee enforced to haue reſpect by recourſe vnto God, the ſole author of all grace. Yea herein we muſt acknowledge Gods power to bee ſuch, as that he is able at his pleaſure to vſe the very cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to be inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of health,<note place="margin">God can vſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very clements to ſtand for the good of his owne.</note> or any other bleſſing in his own appointed time, vnto ſuch as are his own in Chriſt Ieſus: as on the contrary, he is able to make them all ſerue for the manifeſting of his power in wrath, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all ſuch as rebell againſt him,<note place="margin">Euery crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture againſt the wicked.</note> or his Church: as may be ſeene in <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and the congregation of <hi>Choree, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram,</hi> where the water drowned the one, and the earth opened her mouth to ſwallow vp the other. And to conclude, (this being but ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by way of digreſſion) in that he made the muddie and troubled water to heale,<note place="margin">Digreſsion, yet neceſſarie.</note> we note that the Lord oftentimes doth execute his will, and manifeſt his power in mercie, by contrary and vnlikely means in our iudgement.<note place="margin">The Lord of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten healeth by contrary and vnlikly means</note> So <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſha</hi> healed the waters by caſting ſalt into them: whereas naturally ſalt mixed with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bringeth barrenneſſe. Here by the muddy water in this pond was many a man healed: whereas naturally a cleere and chriſtalline wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is more apt for mans health. The like courſe the Lord vſeth in ſpirituall things, he worketh life by death, ioy by ſorrow, exaltation by hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, comforts by the croſſe, peace by
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:7112:26"/>
vvarre:<note place="margin">
                  <p>He ſendeth to hell before he bring to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
                  <p>The end of his ſo doing.</p>
               </note> yea thoſe that hee bringeth to heauen, he firſt maketh them ſaile by hell. And the Lorde doth thus for this eſpeciall ende, that Gods Church may be aſſured, that the Lord is able to execute his will and performe his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, although the meanes or inſtruments of executing the ſame, ſeeme vnto them neuer ſo baſe or vnlike, yea though there appeare to mans iudgement no meanes at all, yet euen then can the Lord our God performe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute that, which he in his eternall wiſedome hath already decreed.</p>
            <p>Now to returne againe into the way from whence we haue digreſſed, this lame man hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of ſo many to bee healed in this pond, came by helpe thither, but being there he was neuer a whit the better: for lying there a long time, ſtill he was preuented of the benefit of the water, becauſe other went downe before him. Here wee ſee he vſed the likely meanes and the lawfull meanes,<note place="margin">Outward, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and lawfull means alwaies preuaile not.</note> and yet had no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe thereby: becauſe it was the purpoſe of God to heale him after a more miraculous manner, for the more ſpeedie conuerſion of the partie healed, and further manifeſtation of his owne glorie. Let vs a little further conſider this matter. This ſicke man vſed the lawfull and likely meane to bee healed of his infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: ſo is it lawfull for thoſe that are ſicke, to vſe the aduice of the Phiſition, and receiue the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:7112:26"/>
hearbes for medicine,<note place="margin">The ſicke may receiue the hearbes for medicine in the Lord, not otherwiſe.</note> ſo farre forth as they are the Lords inſtruments, but no further: and if health come thereby, to giue God the whole honour, as his owne due. Againe, in that hee vſed the likely and lawfull meane to bee hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and yet could not, becauſe God had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laied his recouerie for another end: let euery one of vs make this vſe of it, and thinke, that when we are ſicke, or otherwiſe troubled, and doe vſe the lawfull and outward meanes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted by God for our deliuerance, and yet finde no recouerie thereby, not to murmure,<note place="margin">A neceſſary conſideration.</note> grudge, or thinke with the Atheiſt, God hath forgotten vs: but by the example of this man, to reſt contented, reſoluing with our owne ſoules, that God doth deferre our recouerie for ſome better end, knowne and alreadie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed vpon with the Lord, though hidden and vnknowne to our blind eyes, euen either more miraculouſly to reſtore vs to health againe, for our greater repentance, and more manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his owne power, or elſe fully and final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to worke our deliuerance, by making a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of our fraile tabernacle, and conuey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſoule into the boſome of <hi>Abraham,</hi> I meane the eternall and vnſpeakable ioyes of Gods kingdome.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, in that this man vſed the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and lawfull outward meane for his health, and found none, wee may note a moſt profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:7112:27"/>
doctrine,<note place="margin">Man may pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, but God diſpoſeth.</note> 
               <hi>vz.</hi> that <hi>Paul</hi> may plant, and <hi>Apollo</hi> may water, but it is God that muſt giue the increaſe. The fiſhermen may take great paines in fiſhing all night, and catch iuſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, till Chriſt come and command them to launch into the deepe and make a draught: which done, though before they had tried that place, yet at Chriſts command ſhal they catch an innumerable multitude of fiſhes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 5.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 127.1.2. <hi>Pſal. eodem.</hi>
               </note> Vnleſſe the Lord keepe the houſe, the vvatchmen wake but in vaine. It is but loſt labour to riſe early, and goe late to bed, vnleſſe God bleſſe our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. And therefore all our duties in phiſicke for health,<note place="margin">What courſe we ought to take in all our dealings.</note> in matters for wealth, and in going about ſuch occaſions as are beſeeming our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in this euill world, to commend the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, middle, and iſſue thereof by prayer to almightie God, that hee would ſo direct vs in them, as may ſtand with his glorie, &amp; redound to the comfort of our owne conſciences. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">Note well all the prophane and graceleſſe Atheiſts.</note> note another excellent poynt, which is, that if men walke in their lawfull trades and callings, vſing lawfull and ordinary meanes of deliuerances out of any danger, doe notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding preuaile or profit nothing at all, till God of his mercie giue the bleſſing; what ſhal wee thinke of them, that in ſickneſſe counſell with witches and ſorcerers,<note place="margin">The practiſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch very dangerous.</note> in troubles raiſe vp ſpirits, for things loſt vſe enchauntment, for to haue their ſutes goe forward vſe briberie, for
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:7112:27"/>
their benefices vſe ſymonie, for preferment vſe flatterie, with the Herodians? Yea to conclude, what ſhall we think of all ſuch, as make gaine wrongfully gotten, their god, and wicked and vngodly practiſes the whole courſe of their life; but that euen the heauie iudgement of God hangeth ouer their heads: and as their beginnings and proceedings are in ſin, ſo let them aſſure themſelues, without ſpeedie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, their endings ſhal be in ſame, euen ſudden confuſion both of body &amp; ſoule, with all the reprobates and caſtawaies mentioned in the Scriptures.<note place="margin">A caueat.</note> Let all bold hardy men ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take heede, who enterpriſe many actions without either prayer to the Lord, or warrant of his word.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, it might (in regard of the fleſh) haue been a matter of great griefe vnto this poore ſoule, to ſee all others that came to this poole to be helped, yet he lie ſtill, expecting remedie and found none. Yet hence let vs learne this for our owne vſe, that though we be ſicke, and our neighbours likewiſe, we in trouble, they ſo likewiſe, they are made whole and deliuered, yet we ſtill toſſed to and fro, not likely any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance: and it may bee this befalleth vs, when we are more carefull to ſerue our God then they were, not to be hereat diſmaied, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord (as I haue ſaid before) hath ſecret ends in his eternall purpoſe, of our continued
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:7112:28"/>
afflictions or ſicknes, yea euen ſuch (if wee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide with patience) as ſhall bee to our greater comfort both inwardly and outwardly. And thus much for the third circumſtances to bee noted in his healing, <hi>vz.</hi> what meanes the man vſed himſelf for his recouerie, and found none.</p>
            <p>Of the fourth circumſtance, <hi>vz</hi> by what meanes at length hee was made whole.<note place="margin">The author of his health.</note> The Iſraelites (as it is recorded, Numb. 21.) for their rebellion againſt the Lord, were ſtung and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomed with firie Serpents, a paine moſt into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable, which neither plaiſter or medicine could abate: til at the length vpon the earneſt crie of the people, and <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <hi>Moſes</hi> to make a braſen Serpent,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 21.6.</note> and ſet it vp vpon a pole, with this promiſe, that as for ſinne they were ſtung with a Serpent, ſo whoſoeuer looked vp vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that Serpent which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſo vp, ſhould preſently be healed, and no other way.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 3.</note> Our firſt parent <hi>Adam</hi> tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed God commandement: for a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereof, God inflicted vpon him ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes both in his ſoule and bodie, and which ſhould continue from generation to genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in his whole poſteritie: which ſickneſſes and diſeaſes, as they came vpon vs for the diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of one, ſo can they neuer truly bee healed and taken away, but by the obedience of one man. The firſt man ſinning, and ſo bringing condemnation vpon all, was <hi>Adam.</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:7112:28"/>
The ſecond man fulfilling the law, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by bringing ſaluation to all, that by faith and true repentance accept it, was the man Ieſus Chriſt, a man in all poynts as the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> was, ſinne only excepted.<note place="margin">
                  <p>Donec coeleſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> medicus opem nobis fert, nos non tantum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tùs fouemus multos morbos, ſed etiam mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
                  <p>Caluin in Pſal. <hi>103.</hi> ver. <hi>3. 1.</hi> Ioh. <hi>1.7. 1.</hi> Pet. <hi>1.19.</hi> Rom. <hi>5.4.</hi> Ioh. <hi>14.6.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> He was that imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate lambe of God that taketh away the ſins of the world, and who was the author and ſole worker of this poore mans health. He it is who is the true Phiſition for euery diſeaſed ſoule &amp; body: the plaiſter and very purgation it ſelfe which muſt cleanſe and cleere vs from all our ſinnes whatſoeuer. And who alone is all ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and able to preſent vs holy and pure to God his father: by whom alſo we haue acceſſe vnto the throne of God in our praiers. It is this Chriſt Ieſus, who is the way, the trueth, and the life: vnto whom is giuen a name, in whom muſt bee ſaued all that are regiſtred and writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the booke of life. Here then doe wee ſee, whether all ſicke men, all ſore men, al trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and diſtreſſed men, yea to conclude, all prodigall and ſinfull men muſt reſort to bee healed of their ſickneſſe, eaſed of their griefes, and receiue forgiuenes of their ſinnes, euen to Chriſt Ieſus, the top and roote, beginning and ending, the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apocal.</hi> 1.</note> and the corner ſtone of our ſaluation: and with the halt and lame in the Goſpell, to crie out vnto him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.15.</note> 
               <hi>O Ieſu thou ſonne of Dauid haue mercie on me.</hi> Let the Pope promiſe health by his pardons, the Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciaries
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:7112:29"/>
by their workes,<note place="margin">All meanes of health by man meere mocke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, without Chriſt Ieſus.</note> the Votaries by their vowes, the Heathen by their blind mentions: yet when it comes to the hammering, and the day that euery mans workes ſhall be tryed by fire, they ſhall then finde that all theſe inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted meanes of health, are euen a potion of ranck poyſon prepared by the diuell: and that it is onely the blood of Chriſt Ieſus that muſt purge out the poiſon of the Dragon, &amp; cleanſe vs from all our leproſie whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>This point being moſt pregnant, I might bee very plentifull in proofes out of the word of God for confirmation, in gathering profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table doctrines for inſtruction, and in laying downe many duties for edification: but ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is ſo plaine a point,<note place="margin">Chriſt our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation a plain point.</note> that <hi>propoſuiſſe</hi> is <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmaſſe,</hi> ſo manifeſtly in the word deſcribed, that he that runneth may reade it: ſo ſenſible a matter, that they are paſt feeling who are not touched with it: and finally to all the elect ones of the Lord, a matter of ſuch certaintie, that whoſoeuer doubteth of it,<note place="margin">A moſt certain point for truth</note> he is puft vp in the raging bellowes of his own imaginations: and without ſpeedie repentance, it ſhall be a ſtone to fall vpon them al, of ſuch weight that it ſhall grinde them all to powder. Therefore I will here end it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.28, 29.</note> with Chriſt his large offer to all that lacke helpe: Come vnto Chriſt all ye that labour and are heauy laden &amp; he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh you. Caſt your cares and your diſtreſſed
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:7112:29"/>
cauſes vpon his backe, and reſt contented that he careth for all his owne. And thus much for the fourth circumſtance to bee conſidered in healing the man, which was the meanes, or partie by whom he was healed.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <head>THE SECOND SER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MON OF THE DVTIE OF OVR DELIVERANCE.<note place="margin">The ſecond Sermon.</note>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſecond branch of the exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, <hi>vz.</hi> what was the cauſe of his ſickneſſe, drawne out of theſe words, <hi>ſinne no more:</hi> It appeareth here that ſinne was the cauſe of his ſickneſſe, and ſinne is the cauſe of our troubles, griefes, loſſes, hurts, dangers, or damages whatſoeuer, yea of ſickneſſe, be it of body or of minde. That this may better ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, let vs ſearch out the originall of ſicknes, ſorrow and griefe, and we ſhall finde that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſinne entred, there was neither ſickneſſe; ſorrow, nor griefe: but as ſoone as euer ſinne entred, the other were inflicted, as a iuſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for ſinne. When, where and how ſinne entred, you may finde plainly in Geneſ. 3.<note place="margin">When.</note> It entred euen then when our firſt parents were created in their happie eſtate of innocencie, like to the image of their Creator, perfectly
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:7112:30"/>
righteous in the ſoule, and all the parts thereof throughly ſound in the body, and the conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution thereof, yea both in body and ſoule free from any griefe, vexation or ſorrowe. Sinne entred in Paradiſe,<note place="margin">Where.</note> our parents being placed there.<note place="margin">The meanes.</note> The meanes whereby he entred, was by the ſubtill perſwaſion of the Serpent, the diuels inſtrument, and by our parents volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie hearkening and yeelding thereunto, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey and breake the commandement of their Creator: which ſo ſoone as euer they had done, the curſe of God for the ſame fell vpon our parents for ſin. If we will ſet downe what it is, it is nothing elſe but the tranſgreſſion of the law of God.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.4.</note> Preſently after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tranſgreſſion of the law of God, entred the reward or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of this their tranſgreſſion, which was mortalitie in ſtead of immortalitie,<note place="margin">Mans miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable caſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his fall.</note> weaknes in ſtead of ſtrength, ſicknes in ſtead of health, toyle and trauell in ſtead of continual reſt and peace, ſorrow and ſadnes in ſtead of ioy and comfort: the earth to yeeld nothing but brambles, briers and buſhes (though it bee tilled) in ſtead of plentie of good fruite; to trauaile vp and downe as pilgrimes vpon the face of the earth, in ſtead of perpetual poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of Paradiſe: and though they thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long their toyling daies for a time, yet at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth enforced to yeeld to natures courſe and to dye, in ſtead of liuing for euer the life of the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:7112:30"/>
Angels. All this is apparant in the third of Geneſis.</p>
            <p>You haue heard now the firſt man that euer ſinned, euen <hi>Adam,</hi> the firſt man (that as a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit for his ſinne) euer was ſicke or troubled, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <hi>Adam.</hi> You haue heard what happy caſe he was in before he ſinned, and what wofull e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate hee was in after his fall, a creature full of ſorrow, toyle, trouble, feare, griefe, vexation, digging and deluing, planting and ſowing, and yet but to reape little increaſe: and though hee was before a moſt pleaſant plant of the Lord, ſeated in a moſt fertile ſoyle, yet now through ſin, is he euen become a filthie puddle and ſtanding poole of all iniquitie, a ſeruant to Satan, and a poore priſoner to the diuell.</p>
            <p>Hence let all Gods children learne to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect holineſſe of life,<note place="margin">The vſe.</note> and lothe the life of the wicked: yea euen all the motions, obiects and occaſions of wickedneſſe, ſo farre as the very garment ſtained with ſinne, ſhal be vnto them odious and lothſome. You haue heard now the roote to bee infected, and the bole poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and withall you haue heard the cauſe of this infection. The roote and bole are our firſt parents, they ſinned, and preſently vpon their ſinne came ſhame for a fault, and all kinde of troubles and diſeaſes as their due deſart. Let vs now examine a little whether this poyſon hath not infected all the branches, I meane <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:7112:31"/>
poſteritie, which poſteritie we our ſelues are. Herein let vs conſider that <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uah</hi> were not priuate perſons,<note place="margin">Caluin. in Pſal. <hi>51.</hi> ver. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> but ſuch as had in them the ſtate of the whole world: what good <hi>Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> had, he had it for his whole poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie:<note place="margin">All men in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam haue ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note> what euill ſoeuer hee brought vpon him through ſinne, it was to bee propagated vpon his whole poſteritie. Therefore it is that <hi>Dauid</hi> crieth and ſaith:<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>51.6.</hi> Contra Pelag. qui dicunt pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum non eſſe haereditarium, ſed ſola imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione ex Adamo profectum. Geneſ. <hi>6.5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Behold, in ſinne my mother conceiued me.</hi> Wee bring ſinne with vs from our mothers wombe, and therefore ſickneſſe and ſorrow the ſtipend of ſinne. And the Lord ſaith, <hi>that the imaginations of mans heart are euill continually.</hi> Hereupon it plainly follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that euen al of vs may impute our ſicknes, our ſorrow, weaknes and wants, troubles and torments, dangers, and finally death it ſelfe, to our ſinnes, as the originall and firſt cauſe of them. That ſickneſſe and death did take hold vpon all <hi>Adams</hi> race, euen euery one of vs for ſinne, <hi>Paul</hi> maketh very plaine thus: <hi>By one man ſinne entred into the world, and death by ſin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>and ſo death went ouer all men, for as much as all men haue ſinned.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 18.</note> 
               <hi>And by the offence of one man the fault came ouer all vnto condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>And by one mans diſobedience many were made ſinners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let vs come to proue by example out of the word, how in <hi>Adam</hi> his poſteritie for ſinne, God hath inflicted ſometime ſickneſſe,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:7112:31"/>
ſometime ſores, ſometime troubles of bodie, ſometime griefe of minde. Vpon his owne children, as louing corrections, to make them more diligent ſchollers in Chriſts ſchoole. Vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the wicked, either to draw them to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, (if they belong vnto Gods kingdome) or if they hardned their harts as <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> then to make them euen beginnings of the flaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of hell fire. And firſt let vs ſee out of the word, how for ſinne the Lord hath afflicted his owne Church, with ſickneſſe, trouble, danger, &amp;c. In Geneſ. 6. appeareth, that becauſe the ſonnes of God, contrary to his commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ioyned in mariage with the daughters of men, I meane the wicked ſeede, and for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great ſinnes amongſt them committed: when after a long time of repentance giuen them by the Lord, they would not amend, the Lord deſtroyed them, and the whole world (<hi>Noe</hi> and his familie excepted) with water. When <hi>Dauid</hi> had grieuouſly offended the Lord, with <hi>Berthſhebah</hi> the wife,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.4.17.</note> murther vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Vriah</hi> the husband, and after all this by labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to cloake his ſinne, the Lord therefore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted vpon him theſe troubles. 1. His owne ſonne <hi>Ammon</hi> to defile his ſiſter <hi>Tamar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.14. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 29.30, 31, 32. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.22.</note> and commit inceſt with her. 2. One of his ſonnes to kill another. 3. And in the end as a iuſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence for his adulterie, the Lord ſuffered his owne ſonne <hi>Abſalon</hi> to rebell againſt him,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:7112:32"/>
take away his fathers concubines, and to lye with them. Againe, when <hi>Dauid</hi> in pride of hart numbred his people, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the Lords minde, the Lord for a reward of his ſinne, infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the whole land of Iſrael with the diſeaſe of the peſtilence,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Chro.</hi> 21.14.</note> in ſo much that there dyed of the ſicknes 70. thouſand men.</p>
            <p>O my countrimen, in the Lord Ieſus, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you throughly and ſoundly let vs ſearch to the bottome, the originall and chiefe occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our ſo great and long a viſitation, and I am afraid we ſhall finde, that not <hi>Dauids</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterie, murther, and proud heart alone, haue procured theſe afflictions to fall vpon vs, but a huge maſſe of many infinit ſins more,<note place="margin">A maſſe of ſins amongſt vs crying for vengeance.</note> which this 40. yeeres by-paſt, we haue till now hoor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and treaſured vp againſt our ſelues, till they made ſuch a crye in the Lords eares for vengeance, that (though his mercie be great) yet they haue enforced him at length, to powre out vpon vs the violl of his wrath and by theſe afflictions to manifeſt vnto vs his indignation kindled againſt vs. The Lord giue vs eyes to ſee this, hearts to be ſorie, and a care and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall conſcience, euer hereafter to walke more carefully, as in the Lords preſence.</p>
            <p>To returne againe to <hi>Dauid:</hi> as you haue heard the Lord to haue dealt ſharply with him in outward troubles, for his ſinnes: ſo how he dealt vvith him by inwarde troubles, griefes,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:7112:32"/>
and ſicknes of the minde:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6. <hi>and</hi> 38. <hi>and</hi> 55. <hi>and</hi> 77.</note> his often complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in theſe Pſalmes quoted in the margent, ſufficiently doth witneſſe. Which Pſalmes I wiſh the gentle reader to peruſe and ruminate vpon them, aſſuring him (if he be diſtreſſed in ſoule for ſinne) thereby hee may receiue and finde comfort. The Iſraelites offending God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 21.4, 5, 6.</note> in murmuring againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> the Lords meſſengers, were ſtung with fierie Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, and deſtroyed with the meate in their mouthes. Yea, that excellent woman <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam, Aarons</hi> ſiſter, but once murmuring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.1.2.</note> for marying a woman of Aethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia, and becauſe the Lord talked more fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly with her, then hee did with <hi>Aaron</hi> and her ſelfe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 10.</note> the Lord for this ſinne ſmote her with the diſeaſe of the leproſie, that ſhe was all ouer as white as ſnow,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 14.</note> till that <hi>Moſes</hi> made earneſt ſuite &amp; interceſſion to the Lord for her health. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> was grieuouſly ſicke both in bodie and ſoule,<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 20. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 38.1. 2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 32.14. <hi>Hoſea. chap.</hi> 8. <hi>and chap.</hi> 9.</note> till in mercie God reſtored both to health. Sinne and iniquitie was the cauſe of famine and ſword, threatned to the rebellious Iewes. Often we finde in the Goſpell, that our Sauiour Chriſt giuing ſight to the blinde, or health to the ſick, vſeth this ſpeech, <hi>Go thy way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>thy ſinnes are forgiuen thee:</hi> as if hee ſhould ſay, ſinne hath been the cauſe of thy long ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, but now thy ſins being pardoned, which before as fetters chained thy feete, thou maieſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:7112:33"/>
riſe vp and walke as a ſound man. And of all other moſt excellent and memorable is that of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to the Corinthians,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.30.31</note> where he telleth them, that for the abuſe and prophana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lords Supper amongſt them,<note place="margin">Prophaning of the Lords Supper cauſed death.</note> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them are weake, many ſicke, and many fallen aſleepe, that is, dead. Truly I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that one of the greateſt and capitall crimes, that hath puld theſe plagues vpon our countrie,<note place="margin">This holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prophaned in our North parts of this land. Firſt by the paſtor, &amp; how.</note> and hath made vs a talke in the mouthes of the people of other countries, is the grieuous and monſterous prophanation of this holy Sacrament the Supper of the Lorde, being for ſo long a time ſo horribly propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, both of paſtor and people. The paſtor (or at leaſt hee that occupieth the roome of a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor) without all due care and conſideration, miniſtreth it to all alike without exception, examination, or making any ſeparation of the vnholy from the holy, the prophane from the ſound profeſſor, the dogs and the ſwine from the ſincere and ſanctified people of the Lord: who ought to vſe the power of the keyes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to their calling, if any ſuch vncleane and vnſanctified people doe offer themſelues to communicate, themn by the power aforeſaid, to barre ſuch men from the Supper, vntill there appeare in them teſtimonies of repentance, and change of manners. This being the true and onely remedie preſcribed by Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:7112:33"/>
both againſt ſuch men, and to take away all offences of the Church: and finally to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape the iuſt vengeance of God, that euer fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time haue fallen vpon the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the Goſpell and Sacraments. But alas, thee careles guides and vnſauourie ſalt,<note place="margin">The lets that ſtay them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doing their dutie in this behalfe.</note> either becauſe they are men-pleaſers, dare not: or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they may bee attainted of ſome noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious fault themſelues, wil not: or elſe becauſe they are ſillie, ſimple, ignorant ſots, and know not how to doe it, doe ſtill continue in their careles courſe, to the vtter deſtruction of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and many a poore ſoule vnder their charge,<note place="margin">The poore ſoules in great danger hereby</note> vnleſſe God in his great mercie take pitie vpon them. Theſe euill workers, nay ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther betrayers of the ſillie ſheepe of Chriſt, either know not, or at leaſt care not for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny inuectiues, as the godly fathers in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages of the Church, haue giuen out moſt boldly, both by word and writing againſt the paſtors, who ſuffer ſuch monſterous propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the holy Supper of the Lord: as alſo the great care that Chriſtian Churches haue ſtill had, to keepe themſelues cleane from that pollution. Amongſt the multitude of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly writers, I cannot paſſe ouer but ſet downe that moſt excellent ſaying of <hi>Iohn Chryſoſtome</hi> in his Homilies vpon <hi>Matthew</hi> concerning this point, whoſe words are theſe:<note place="margin">Chryſoſt in hom. <hi>38.</hi> in Mat. c. <hi>27</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>No ſmall puniſhment hangeth ouer your heads, if knowing
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:7112:34"/>
any man to bee taken in wickedneſſe, you ſuffer him to be partaker hereof, for his blood ſhall be required at your hands. Therefore if any Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, if the Conſul himſelfe, if he that weareth the crowne come vnworthily barre him &amp; keepe him backe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Againſt the vnlawfull fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of any.</note> 
               <hi>thou haſt greater authoritie then he. Therefore if a moſt cleere ſpring of water were committed vnto thee, to keepe it onely to ſerue the flocke, when thou diddeſt ſee beaſts vſe to ſtrike and gore, and moſt filthie ſwne come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it, thou wouldeſt not ſuffer them to goe downe into the water, nor to trouble the ſpring. And now when as the moſt hallowed ſpring, not of water, but of blood and the holy Ghoſt is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto thee, if thou ſhalt ſee men notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly defiled with ſinne come vnto it, wilt thou not be angrie, nor forbid them?</hi> And a little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he ſaith, <hi>If you will feare men, he will laugh at you; if God, you ſhall be reuerenced of men. Surely I will rather yeeld my bodie to death, and ſuffer my blood to be ſhed, then to be partaker of this pollution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the example of the practiſe of Chriſtian Churches, one example likewiſe ſhall ſuffice, which ſhall bee the example of the Greeke Church in former times,<note place="margin">The example of the Greeke Church. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. A congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the faithfull.</note> who had ſuch a reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent eſtimation of this holy banket, that the very name wherewith they called it, argueth the ſame. Firſt, <hi>Vocarunt eam</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: that is to to ſay, a congregation of the faithfull, which
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:7112:34"/>
was ſo religiouſly obſerued: <hi>Quod quamuis tolerabantur in concion. publicis prophani, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rùm vbi inchoanda erat ipſa Dominicae caenae communicatio, iubebantur illi diſcedere, &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedere &amp;c.</hi> Although the wicked and open prophane were permitted to bee preſent at their publike preachings &amp; ſermons: yet when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the Supper of the Lord was to bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred, then they vſed theſe words: Depart ye wicked and prophane, and draw neere ye that truly and ſincerely profeſſe Chriſt and his Goſpell. Againe, <hi>Vocarunt eam</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:<note place="margin">A holy table.</note> they called it a holy table, both in regard of the holy and heauenly foode of the ſoule there of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered: as alſo in regard of thoſe holy people, who alone are admitted to the eating there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. So that theſe being well conſidered, I will conclude this point concerning the paſtors abuſe in the aforeſaid prophanation, with this earneſt wiſh: that all who are called to this waightie calling of the worke of the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, with care and conſcience ſo to behaue themſelues therein, as they that ſhall giue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count in the great day of the Lord for euery ſoule that hath periſhed within their charge, through their negligence.</p>
            <p>For the peoples prophaning this holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">Secondly it is prophaned by the people, and how.</note> I my ſelfe haue bin oft an eye witneſſe (God is my record) to my griefe, when I haue ſeene great multitudes of people in the houſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:7112:35"/>
of the Lord,<note place="margin">My ſelf an eye witneſſe.</note> with ſtriuing, thronging, &amp; preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing forwarde, contend who ſhould firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the outwarde elements at the hands of their miniſter, making no better then a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon banket of it, or as though they were in extreame haſte. Againe, the Parſons proctor to be reckoning for his fees in the very time of adminiſtring the Supper,<note place="margin">Great propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and worthie pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</note> and that within the Lords houſe, not farre from the miniſter, as great a noiſe of brauling about him, as of ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Pſalmes amongſt the Communicants: yea farre greater, for the one is often vſed, the other very ſeldome or neuer. I might bee large in laying downe ſuch manifold abuſes as theſe,<note place="margin">Many moe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides theſe.</note> which I haue ſeene with mine eyes, as euery one after they haue gotten their rightings (for ſo our ſillie ignorant people call it) to haſten out of the congregation, neuer reuerently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding till all be partakes, that they might all depart with a ioynt thankſgiuing. But theſe are ſufficient to the reader, to teſtifie how iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I am perſwaded,<note place="margin">Ex vnguibus leonem aſtima.</note> that for theſe and ſuch like abuſes, the Lorde hath rightly plagued our countrie. After the receiuing of this holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament and ſeale of the true Chriſtians ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, they hold on <hi>à malo in peius,</hi> they then goe for good fellowſhip to the tauerne or ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe altogether,<note place="margin">The Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, a great cauſe of theſe abuſes.</note> and thence they come not till they are inflamed and made drunke with ſtrong drinke, and then out they muſt, but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:7112:35"/>
then they came in: for now they run out to purge themſelues and their heauie ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mackes, by belchings and beaſtly vomiting: others to brawle and fight: ſo as it would wound a Chriſtians hart, to ſee how the ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſoules, worſe then brute beaſts,<note place="margin">This cryeth for vengea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, without ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy repentance</note> doe in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing the bread and wine at the Supper of the Lord, eate and drinke their owne condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>Others there be, more niſe in outward ſhew,<note place="margin">As euill as the other.</note> it may be will walke ſolitary that day, abſtaine in outwarde appearance from their wonted courſe of ſinne: but if they do this for one day, two were too many, and therefore the morow after the Supper, is as the day before, euen to drinke ſinne like water, and draw iniquitie as it were with cartropes.</p>
            <p>A third ſort of vnworthie receiuers there be in our countrie, whom I may very well call carnall goſpellers, and lip-profeſſors,<note place="margin">Too many of ſuch amongſt vs.</note> who doe receiue this holy Supper together with Gods deare children, and thereby doe make their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne profeſſion of newnes of life: but after a ſeaſon it proueth rather worſe with them then with the former: for they are ſuch, that though they crie, Lord, Lord, <hi>voce:</hi> yet they deny to doe the will of their heauenly father,<note place="margin">What dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous effect follow ſuch wicked dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</note> 
               <hi>vita:</hi> and ſo are an occaſion to the wicked and profeſſed enemies of Gods trueth, of blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming that glorious Goſpel of Chriſt Ieſus,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:7112:36"/>
whereof they make profeſſion, though vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoundly, and after an vncleane manner. Theſe men, to ſpeake plainly, they are very neere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, if not the ſame men whereof Chriſt teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.</note> that they expulſe out the vncleane ſpirit: but after a ſeaſon the ſame ſpirit returneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, he bringeth ſeuen other ſpirits with him worſe then himſelfe, and finding all cleane ſwept and garniſhed, they reenter and take poſſeſſion in the man, and make their dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling there: whoſe latter end <hi>(horrendum dictu)</hi> is worſe then the beginning. And ſuch as <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> painteth out,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 20</note> who after they haue in ſhew throwne and ſhaken off ſinne, and bidden the world adiew, doe notwithſtanding after all this, enter couenant to bee Satans ſeruant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, in whom the prouerbe is too true:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 22.</note> 
               <hi>The dogge is returned to his vomit, and the ſow that was waſhed to her wallowing in the mare.</hi> The Lord for his mercies ſake,<note place="margin">Amen, Amen.</note> work reformation hereof both in paſtor and people: which refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation if preſently it appeare not, I feare me a worſe day,<note place="margin">I feare the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quell.</note> then hitherto hath been ſeene, will inſue: whereof more at large hereafter. And let this ſuffice alſo for proofes out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word, how the Lord for ſinne ſendeth troubles and ſickneſſes, both of body and minde vpon his owne people.</p>
            <p>Let vs now in a word ſhew how he doth it vpon the wicked: wherein I may fitly vſe the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:7112:36"/>
ſpeech of the Apoſtle, that <hi>if for ſinne iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment begin at the houſe of God, what ſhall be the end of the wicked?</hi>
               <note place="margin">A fearfull end without all doubt.</note> And if hee deale thus with the greene tree, what may wee thinke will be the end of the drie and withered tree, but to be caſt into the fire and burnt vp for euer?</p>
            <p>And firſt, moſt famous and worthie of all memorie is the example of Gods iudgement vpon <hi>Ioab</hi> and al his poſteritie,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.29.</note> for murthering ſo cruelly and deceitfully two valiant Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, <hi>Abner</hi> and <hi>Amaſa,</hi> as appeareth in their ſtories at large: where <hi>Dauid</hi> thus threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the iudgement of the Lord againſt him, and his whole poſteritie, ſaying: <hi>Let the blood of Abner fall on the head of Ioab, and on all his fathers houſe: that the houſe or iſſue of Ioab be neuer without ſome that haue running iſſues, or a leper, or that leaneth on a ſtaffe or that falleth on the ſword, or that lacketh bread.</hi> Loe here how many wayes, for this bloodie fact, God will plague &amp; puniſh him. Firſt with running <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> iſſues, a ſore diſeaſe. With leproſie, a ſorer if it <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> can be. With lamenes, meant by leaning on <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> a ſtaffe. Blood for blood, according to the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Lord his threatning: <hi>He that ſheddeth mans blood, by man ſhall his blood be ſhed againe.</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> meant by lacking of bread: and <hi>Cain</hi> for ſhedding the innocent blood of his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Abel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 4.</note> vvas both he and his poſteritie made runnagates ouer the face of the whole earth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:7112:37"/>In the 7. and 8. of Exodus, you ſhall finde how oft the Lorde plagued <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and the whole land, for cruelly oppreſſing his people, euen with ten principall plagues: there withall their great and capitall offences.<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 13.</note> So he dryed the hand of king <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> when he ſtretched it out againſt the Prophet of the Lord to take him.<note place="margin">Take heede of this, the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous men that haue long no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to ſmell your profit a farre off.</note> 
               <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Iezebel,</hi> becauſe vniuſtly they tooke away <hi>Naboth</hi> his vineyard, and lead a great number a whoring after ſtrange gods, the Lord cauſed <hi>Iezebels</hi> daintie carkaſſe to be eaten vp of dogs, by the wall of <hi>Izreel:</hi> yea, that his poſteritie ſhould neuer haue the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of a comely buriall: but if they dyed in the citie,<note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 21.25. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 9.10. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 24.10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.3.4.</note> the dogs ſhould deuoure them: and if in the field, the foules of the ayre ſhould eate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp. Euen as the Lorde executed his fierce wrath vpon all <hi>Ieroboam</hi> his ſeede: and vpon the whole houſe of <hi>Baaſha,</hi> for their Idolatrie. Let all couetous cormorants, and Idolatrous whoremongers repent, for feare the like iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould fall vpon them.<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 1. <hi>ver.</hi> 1 2, 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Ahaziah</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing gotten a fall through a lattiſe window, and hurt himſelfe very ſore, deſpaired of helpe from the true God, and therefore ſent meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to enquire of the god of Ekron, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his recouerie: which thing was ſo abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable to the Lord, that he ſent a meſſenger vnto him, to tell him, that he ſhould not come downe from the bed whereon he lay, but dye
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:7112:37"/>
the death.<note place="margin">In our ſicknes ſeeke vnto none but God. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 6.</note> Beware in our ſickneſſe wee ſeeke not vnlawfull meanes for our recouerie. The King of Syria his hoſt comming to take the Prophet in <hi>Dothan,</hi> the Lord for their boldnes ſmote them all with blindneſſe. A dangerous matter to attempt the perſecuting of Gods children. <hi>Gehezi</hi> for coueting that vnlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 5.27.</note> which his maſter had refuſed of <hi>Naaman</hi> religiouſly, when it was offered, was ſmitten with a leproſie. And of all other,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 21.18.19.</note> moſt fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is the ſickneſſe and death wherewith the Lord ſmote <hi>Jehoram,</hi> for vnnaturall murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his brethren, and for abominable Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie: he ſmote him with an incurable diſeaſe, euen the diſeaſe of his bowels: ſo that day by day, through the diſeaſe, his bowels fell out: ſo after the end of two yeeres, continuing in this ſore diſeaſe, his guts fell out with the diſeaſe. And laſtly of <hi>Herod,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 12.25.</note> how horrible a thing to bee heard, that for his pride, and arrogating glorie to himſelf, which was only due to God,<note place="margin">Pride wil haue a fall.</note> was moſt fearefully throwne downe from his throne of eſtate, and deuoured of wormes.</p>
            <p>To leaue the teſtimonies of the word, and to come to the demonſtration of Gods feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full viſitations by ſtrange ſickneſſes,<note place="margin">Examples of Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments vpon wicked perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors of the Church.</note> againſt wicked perſecutors of Chriſts Church, &amp; blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers of his name, recorded and ſpoken of in ancient hiſtories, let this bee the firſt. One <hi>Henry,</hi> a famous Archbiſhop of <hi>Mentz,</hi> a
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:7112:39"/>
vertuous and wel diſpoſed prelate, being moſt cruelly dealt withall by the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> and his ſubſtitutes, and being debarred of all lawfull proceeding and iudgement in law a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, mildly anſwered the wicked Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges thus: Seeing that neither by appeale to the Apoſtolike ſea, nor by your vpright ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of your ſelues, I can haue my innocencie tried, I appeale to the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, as to the moſt high and iuſt Iudge,<note place="margin">A righteous appeale.</note> and cite you before his iudgement, there to anſwer me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the high Iudge: for neither iuſtly nor vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly, but by corruption (as it pleaſeth you) you haue iudged. Whereunto they ſcoffingly anſwered; Goe you firſt, and we will follow. Not long after the ſaid <hi>Henry</hi> dyed: whereof the two Cardinals, that were the wicked Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, hauing intelligence, ſaid one to the other ieſtingly: Behold he is gone before, and vvee muſt follow after according to our promiſe. And verely they ſaid truer then they were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of:<note place="margin">A terrible ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample for cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Iudges to beware.</note> for within a while they dyed both in one day. For the one ſitting vpon a Iakes to eaſe himſelfe, voyded out all his guts into the draught, and miſerably ended his life. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gnawing off the fingers of his hands, and ſpitting them out of his mouth (all deformed in deuouring himſelfe) dyed. And one <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nold,</hi> who became a falſe Iudas to the good Archbiſhop, in accuſing of him, when hee
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:7112:39"/>
ſhould haue excuſed him:<note place="margin">Anno Do. <hi>1105.</hi> Ex Helmoldo &amp; Gotfrido Viter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bienſi. &amp; Act. &amp; Mon. Fox. pag. <hi>196.</hi>
               </note> ſhortly after dyed likewiſe, and for certaine daies lying ſtinking vpon the ground vnburied, was open to the ſpoyle of euery raſcall and harlot.</p>
            <p>The like horrible and fearfull ſtroke of Gods hand, was executed vpon a wicked papiſt and perſecutor of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good Merindolians in France, who was called <hi>Iohn de Roma:</hi> this wicked wretch, of meere malice againſt the trueth, plagued the poore proteſtants of Merindoll, with a ſtrange and vnwonted kind of torment, wherein hee moſt delighted, and moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly practiſed: he filled bootes with boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling greaſe, and put them vpon the legges of Chriſtians, tying them backward to a forme, with their legges hanging downe ouer a ſmall fire: and in this torment he examined them of their faith, belike thinking by this intolerable paine, to make them reuolt from their faith. This monſter at length hauing almoſt finiſhed the date of his wicked daies, fell ſicke of a moſt horrible diſeaſe, ſtrange and vnknowne to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Phiſition: ſo vnnaturall were the paynes, wherewith he was continually vexed in all his bodie, that no oyntment, no fomentation, nor any thing elſe could eaſe him one minute of an houre: neither was there any man could tarrie neere about him, nor yet would any of his friends come neere him, ſo great was the ſtinch that came from him. For which cauſe he
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:7112:38"/>
was carried from the Iacobines to an hoſpitall there to bee kept. But the ſtinch and infection there ſo increaſed, that no man there durſt come neere him: neither was he himſelfe able to abide the horrible ſtinch that iſſued from his owne bodie, full of vlcers and ſores, and ſwarming with vermine, and ſo rotten, that the fleſh fell from the bone by peece meale. Whileſt he was in theſe torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts and anguiſh, he cried out often in great rage: Oh who will kill me?<note place="margin">Act. &amp; Mon. pag. <hi>945.</hi>
               </note> who will rid and deliuer me out of theſe intolerable paines, which I know I ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for the euils and oppreſſions that I haue done to the poore men? In theſe horrible tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and fearefull deſpayre, this blaſphemer and cruell homicide ended his vnhappie daies and curſed life; as a ſpectacle to all perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, receiuing a iuſt reward of his crueltie by the iuſt iudgement of God. Being dead, none would come neere to burie him; but a Frier of his owne order, with a hooke caught bold of his ſtinking carkaſſe, and drew him into a hole of the earth.</p>
            <p>The like fearfull iudgement was vpon the Lord of <hi>Reueſt,</hi> being chiefe preſident of the parliament of <hi>Aix,</hi> putting many a good chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to death: afterward was himſelfe ſtriken with ſuch an horrible ſickneſſe, that for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie thereof, his wiſe, or any that were about him,<note place="margin">Pag. eadem.</note> durſt not come neere him, and ſo dyed in
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:7112:38"/>
this furie and rage. The like fearefull ſudden death had <hi>Barthol. Caſſaneus,</hi> who ſucceeded the other both in place and perſecution. I can not but ſet downe likewiſe a note of another bloodie perſecutor of the poore Merindoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>Iohn Miniers</hi> Lorde of <hi>Opede,</hi> whoſe iudgement from the Lord, for ſhedding ſo much innocent blood, was a ſtrange kinde of bleeding in his nether parts,<note place="margin">Like for like.</note> like to a bloodie iſſue or flux: and not being able to voyde any vrine,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 953.</note> till by little and little his guts at length within him rotted, and his intrals began to be eaten vp of wormes. In which extremitie,<note place="margin">The wicked in their extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties howle and cry moſt deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratly.</note> raging and caſting out blaſphemous words, and feeling a fire burne within him, from the nauill vpward, with extreame ſtinch of his lower parts, at length finiſhed his wretched life.</p>
            <p>The like may be ſaid of one of the accuſers of <hi>Narciſſus,</hi> the good old Biſhop of <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> who wiſhed if his vntrue accuſation were not true, that he might ſhortly fall into ſome great and grieuous ſicknes: which wiſh moſt fearfully afterward was executed vpon him,<note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> and that ſhortly after being ſtriken with a ſore ſickneſſe from top to toe, and ſo dyed.</p>
            <p>And to conclude this point, the like may be ſaid, concerning the ſudden death of one <hi>Nightingale</hi> parſon of <hi>Crondall</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> who was made by the Cardinals authoritie, chiefe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:7112:40"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:7112:40"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:7112:41"/>
Penitentiary of that Deanry. He comming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the pulpit vpon a Shroue Sunday, read pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely the Popes bull of pardon that was ſent into <hi>England,</hi> moſt blaſphemouſly vttering theſe words: That he fully beleeued, that by the vertue of that Bull, he was as cleane from ſinne,<note place="margin">Intolerable blaſphemie.</note> as that night he was borne: immediatly vpon the ſame, fell ſuddenly dovvne out of the pulpit, and neuer ſtirred more hand or foote.</p>
            <p>Theſe are ſufficient to proue vnto you this point, how the Lord for ſinne inflicteth vpon the wicked, ſickneſſes, diſeaſes, and troubles of the body. And how he dealeth moſt feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in tormenting their conſciences, I referre you ouer to <hi>Cain,</hi> who ſuppoſed euery man would kill him that met him.<note place="margin">Both body &amp; ſoule plagued in the wicked by the Lord for their ſins.</note> To <hi>Saul,</hi> who wiſhed himſelfe ſlaine. To <hi>Achitophel</hi> and <hi>Iudas,</hi> who hanged themſelues: and the too many experienced teſtimonies in our owne times both of men and women, that hauing been plunged to deſperation, at the view of their horrible iniquities, haue been the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their owne death themſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A Catalog of them all.</note>Let vs now as in a little Catalogue ſet down all theſe ſeuerall ſinnes aforenamed, ſo ſeuere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puniſhed by the Lorde in ſeuerall wicked men, that ſo the diligent reader may more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily beare them away, to make him euer here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after learne by other mens harmes to beware: and my propounded propoſition bee by ſo
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:7112:41"/>
many clowdes of witneſſes ratified and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed: ſo to continue herafter without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolement.</p>
            <p>Murther and ſhedding of innocent blood,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <note place="margin">Murther.</note> puniſhed in the offender and his poſteritie with the ſtate of a runnagate as in <hi>Cain:</hi> with running iſſues, lamenes, blood for blood, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie: as in <hi>Ioab</hi> and his poſteritie.</p>
            <p>Hardues of heart, and contempt of Gods <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> word puniſhed with loſſe of goods,<note place="margin">Hardnes of heart.</note> as corne and cattell: yea loſſe of children, as in <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Stretching the hand to make our authority <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> hurt Gods meſſengers,<note place="margin">Abuſing of authoritie to perſecution.</note> puniſhed with withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and drying vp the hand, as in <hi>Ieroboam:</hi> and puniſhed with the blindnes in the king of Syria his ſeruants.</p>
            <p>Couetouſneſſe, oppreſſion, and killing,<note place="margin">Couetouſnes, oppreſsion and killing.</note> to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> come by their purpoſe vnlawfully, and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie ioyned there withal, puniſhed in the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and their poſteritie, neuer to haue the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of a comely buriall: but dying in the citie, to bee eaten vp of dogs: or dying in the field, to be deuoured with the foules of the ayre: as in <hi>Ahab, Iezebell,</hi> and their poſteritie.</p>
            <p>Pride and exalting of our ſelues againſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> God puniſhed,<note place="margin">Pride and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alting againſt God.</note> by making the offender like a brute beaſt, as in <hi>Nabuchadnezaar.</hi> And with a fearfull ſudden death, as in <hi>Herod.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:7112:42"/>
               <note place="margin">Deſpaire of Gods helpe in extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note>Deſpayring of Gods helpe in our ſickneſſe, and ſeeking the helpe of falſe gods, puniſhed with neuer recouerie of health: but dying of it, as in <hi>Ahaziah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/>
               <note place="margin">Extreme co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſnes.</note>A couetous heart that cannot bee content to forgoe any profit, if they may haue it, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it ſtand with a good conſcience or no, and often ioyned with lying, puniſhed by the Lord with leproſie for euer: as in <hi>Gehezi, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſha</hi> his ſeruant.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>King.</hi> 16. Idolatrie in our ſelues and drawing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers vnto it.</note>To commit Idolatry our ſelues, and by our perſwaſion, or power, to draw others to doe the like, puniſhed in <hi>Bataſha</hi> and his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</p>
            <p>Vnnaturall murthering of our kindred, ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> with groſſe Idolatrie,<note place="margin">Vnnaturall murther. 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.13.14.15.16.</note> moſt fearefully plagued with the diſeaſe of the bowels incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and in the end the guts to fall out, as in <hi>Iehoram.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/>
               <note place="margin">Deſperation.</note>Deſperation of Gods mercies, puniſhed with killing and hanging themſelues: as in <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Iudas.</hi> Corruption in iudgement, and condemning the innocent without a cauſe, plagued with fearful and ſudden death, as hath been ſhewed by the example of the Cardinals, iudges of the good Archbiſhop of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/>
               <hi>Mentz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Strang and vnnaturall perſecution.</note>Vnnaturall and not heard of before per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution againſt the poore ſaints, plagued with
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:7112:42"/>
ſtrange and vnwonted diſeaſes: as in <hi>Iohn de Roma,</hi> a Iacobine, the Lord of <hi>Reueſt,</hi> and the Lord of <hi>Opede.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Blaſphemous derogating from the crowne <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> and dignitie of Chriſt Ieſus,<note place="margin">Blaſphemies.</note> the waſhing away of ſinnes in all men, and arrogating the ſame to the Pope and his pardons, plagued with ſudden and preſent death, as in the parſon of <hi>Crondall</hi> aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, let vs by ſome few proofes out of the word, confirme this which hath been illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated, both out of the examples of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and the Acts and Monuments of our owne Church. In the 29.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.22.</note> chapter of Deutero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, verſ. 22. <hi>Moſes</hi> ſheweth, that the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Iſraelites which was then for to come, and the ſtrangers that ſhould come from a farre land, ſhall ſay when they ſee the plagues and diſeaſes of this land, wherewith the Lord ſhall ſmite it:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 24. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 25.</note> 
               <hi>Wherefore hath the Lord done thus vnto this land? And they ſhall anſwer, Becauſe they haue forſaken the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the Lord God of their fathers, which he made with them.</hi> And chapter 31.17.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 31.17.</note> 
               <hi>They ſhall be conſumed, and many aduerſities and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations ſhall come vpon them. Then they ſhall ſay, Are not theſe troubles come vpon vs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God is not with vs?</hi> Of all other places in the Scriptures, let the 28. of Deuteronomie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 26.</note> and the 26. of Leuit. be as glaſſes for all men
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:7112:43"/>
to behold themſelues in: where you ſhal find, for diſobedience and breach, of Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, the Lord will inflict vpon them moſt extreame diſeaſes, and ſores of the body: as the peſtilence,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 21.22 <hi>Verſ.</hi> 27.</note> a conſumption, the feuer, the burning ague, the botch of Egypt, the Eme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodes, the ſcab, and the itch. He threatned to ſmite them in the knees,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 35.</note> &amp; in the thighs, with a ſore botch, that they could not bee healed, euen from the ſole of their foote to the top of their head. For other griefes of body, and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the mind, that there is threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt the obſtinate offenders: I wiſh the godly to peruſe them, thereby to be as bridles and ſtayes vnto them, whenſoeuer Satan by his ſuggeſtions, laboureth to driue them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto.<note place="margin">Take the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer with the ſweete.</note> And I wiſh that the wicked would (in their boldnes to drinke vp ſinne like water) once giue a glance backe to theſe fearefull threats of the Lord, and view what ſhall be the wofull ende of their groſſe and abominable wickedneſſes. I wiſh alſo that both theſe, and all the aforenamed proofes, together with the manifold examples out of the Scriptures, and ſundry hiſtories of the Church before allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,<note place="margin">Let them be for a Chriſtian Chronicle.</note> be in ſtead of a little Chronicle for all ſick and ſore men, either in body or minde, for all thoſe that are ſtrangely viſited, or grieuouſly afflicted, to be exerciſed in: wherein they may finde the Lords iudgements fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:7112:43"/>
executed vpon the wicked and abominable li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, without abatement, controlement, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, fearing no power,<note place="margin">The wicked neuer able to ſtay Gods iudgements.</note> preuented by no policie, ſtayed by no bribes, nor abated by any medicine: till ſuch time as hee hath layed the honors, houſes, habitations and whole poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities of the wicked euen with the ground.<note place="margin">The end of the wicked.</note> As may be ſeene of <hi>Ieroboam, Baaſha, Ahab,</hi> and <hi>Ioab,</hi> that I ſay men viſited with ſicknes, vpon a ſound ſauerie of the premiſſes, may without delay enter into a ſerious ſpeech, and due con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of their owne eſtate, in regarde of ſinne:<note place="margin">Search ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing your ſelues.</note> and if they finde that ſuch ſinnes as you haue heard here before to bee plagued of the Lord, to rule and raigne in them, or any ſinne and tranſgreſsion of Gods commandements, then let them impute the cauſe of their viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to their owne ſinnes, and wicked conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, reſoluing further, that he will not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw it, who hath ſent it, hee will not heale them, who hath wounded them, they ſhall not recouer of their ſickneſſe, nor come downe from the bed whereon they lie, till ſuch time as the Lord ſee them broken hearted with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid;</hi> and vowing to his maieſtie, the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſacrifice of a better life, or at leaſt, if they paſſe that diſeaſe or fit (vnleſſe they from the heart repent) let them looke ere it be long,<note place="margin">One being gone, another will come, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent.</note> to come vnder the extremitie of ſome other: that ſhall be as a beaſome in his wrath to take all away. Laſt of all, I wiſh euen from my very
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:7112:44"/>
heart roote in Ieſus Chriſt: that all of you my Countriemen (for whoſe comfort eſpecially I was moued, to pen this little vnworthie trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe) may ſearch, and throughly ranſacke your hearts to the bottome: for theſe ſinnes, <hi>vz.</hi> Murther, contempt of Gods word, perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Gods children, couetouſnes, oppreſſion, killing, pride, deſpairing of Gods power: Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie, lying againſt ones owne conſcience, deſpairing of Gods mercies, which ſinnes flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing in the reprobates, haue been fearefully plagued as you haue heard before.<note place="margin">Search till we finde them, for they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs.</note> Search fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for wicked and vnlawfull mariages: for whoredome, murmuring againſt Gods faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full magiſtrates or miniſters. And ſo the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous profanation of the ſupper of the Lord: ſinnes for committing whereof, the Lord hath grieuouſlie puniſhed his owne people, as plainely hath been proued: yea and for many moe, then all theſe would I haue you, with your ſelues to make a particular and ſtrict ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination,<note place="margin">Pray you ſo likewiſe. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.17.18.</note> and I beſeech God, euen the father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that the eyes of your vnderſtanding may be enlightened, that you may diſcerne and clearely ſee how farre you haue entred a couenant, and bound your ſelues in league with moſt of theſe ſinnes, and many other moſt abhominable ſinnes;<note place="margin">Ouer all ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally. In many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> as your hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Atheiſme, affected ignorance, groſſe Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie: and in moſt places mocking, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:7112:44"/>
the Lords ordinarie meanes of your ſaluation: in ſeeing of them, acknowledge your long and continued afflictions, to be ſweete corrections,<note place="margin">The Lord hath dealt ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilie with you, as yet.</note> in regarde of that fearefull and dreadfull condemnation, they haue long ſince before this cried for, as a ſtipend of deſert due vnto them; yea in vtter loathing of them, and heartie griefe for offending God by them: let vs all crie with the prodigall childe: that for our ſinnes we are not worthy to haue the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens to couer vs, the earth to beare vs,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.21.</note> 
               <hi>Iehouah</hi> to protect vs, or Ieſus Chriſt euer to be a Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our vnto vs: yet here not to ſtay, but in hope as our anker, through faith, as our hand, by the promiſe of the reueiled word for our certainty to preaſe and poſt forward, and with the Eagle to ſoare vp to the true phiſition of our ſoules, for healing our ſickneſſes, the good Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane to bind vp our wounds, the euerlaſting high Prieſt, for bearing our infirmities, euen Ieſus Chriſt the righteous: that thereby our ſinnes, the originall of our ſickneſſes, may be blotted out and cleane clenſed: and from Chriſt we may heare this comfortable voyce: <hi>Ariſe and walke, &amp;c. Be whole, for thy ſins are forgiuen thee.</hi> My beloued in the Lord,<note place="margin">No ſounde courſe but this to ſaue vs from periſhing.</note> except this through courſe be taken, neuer looke for ſauing, ſound, and continuing health; but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen with <hi>Gehezi</hi> to die a leprous man. Now as I haue ſpoken of particular men, for parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:7112:45"/>
ſinnes diuerſly diſeaſed: ſo may I ſpeake of whole countries, kingdomes and places, who for ſin and iniquitie haue been plagued. Some with ſudden deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 19.</note> as Sodom &amp; Gomor. Some with captiuitie, as the Iſraelites vnder the Babylonians.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 36.</note> Some with hauing the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, wiſe, and aged Counſellors taken from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as <hi>Eſay</hi> threatneth the Iewes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 8.1.2.3.4 1. <hi>King.</hi> 20. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 6.19. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 17.29.</note> Some with death and famine, as was Samaria and Ieruſalem, and as this our nation of late: and ſome with the diſeaſe of the peſtilence, burning ague, and bloody iſſues, as this our owne land: firſt, not long ſince in the South parts:<note place="margin">We haue felt the ſame.</note> and now theſe two yeres laſt paſt in our Northerne parts. And ſeeing it hath been proued, that theſe correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and puniſhments flow from our owne diſobedience and wilfull rebellion,<note place="margin">From whence theſe puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments flowe.</note> therefore if euer the effect wee deſire to haue remoued, let vs firſt take away the cauſe, which is our ſinnes,<note place="margin">Sublata cauſa tollitur effectus.</note> and aſſure our ſelues the effect will ceaſe, which is Gods fearefull puniſhments. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> Theſe proofes, examples, and vſes being thus laid downe, this doctrine following ſhall bee the concluſion of it, <hi>vz.</hi> what euill ſoeuer wee ſuffer either in body or minde, we may impute it to our ſinnes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38.5.</note> as the originall and firſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion thereof: whereupon may bee gathered a ſecond doctrine.<note place="margin">Caluin. in Ioh. cap. <hi>5.</hi> verſ. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Non ſunt fortunae hominum calamitates, ſed totidem ſunt caſtigatoriae feru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lae:</hi> Our ſickneſſes, diſeaſes, or griefes, bee they
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:7112:45"/>
inward or outward, proceed not from fortune, or by chance:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos.</hi> 3.6.</note> but by the foredecreed counſell of the higheſt, that they may bee as ſo many checkes vnto the pride of our ſinnes: the truth hereof being granted, there enſueth an excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding comfort to the conſcience,<note place="margin">A comfort.</note> carefull of Gods ſeruice, <hi>vz.</hi> that our heauenly father ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth no delight, nor pleaſure in puniſhing vs: and therefore doth hee neuer ſeuerely ſcourge vs,<note place="margin">Calu. ibid.</note> but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is highly offended by our tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, and perforce vrged to change mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie into iudgement,<note place="margin">The Lord is haled on to iudgement by our ſinnes.</note> &amp; his louing countenance into ſeuere corrections. And thus much gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally haue I ſet downe, and proued the cauſe and originall of ſickneſſe, ſorrowes, troubles and death itſelf in all men liuing vpon the face of the earth, as they are <hi>Adams</hi> branches and poſteritie.</p>
            <p>Now leaſt the godly man (for conſcience ſake perſecuted, or for his further triall of the Lord afflicted) ſhould be too much diſmaied, and thinke his perſecutions were but iuſt plagues for ſinne, and his croſſes no comforts, contrary to the ſweete promiſes of the Goſpel in that behalfe:<note place="margin">How and for what end af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions are laid vpon the godly.</note> therefore let vs ſearch how and in what ſort they are laid vpon the godly. The nature and condition of all troubles both of body and minde, in reſpect of their firſt origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, are qualified to the children of God and true Chriſtians: not by any dignitie, or deſert
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:7112:46"/>
at all of their owne, but as <hi>Eliſha</hi> healed the bitter and venemous waters, by caſting ſalt into them:<note place="margin">Note well.</note> ſo the bitter and intolerable ſting of death, the bitter and vnſauorie ſickneſſes and diſeaſes both of our bodies and our ſoules are healed, the nature of them changed, the poyſon remoued, by the ſauourie ſalt of Chriſt his blood: yea, all ſicke, halt, lame, and withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red men, haue their griefes eaſed, by the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, perſecuted, ſcorned, ſcoffed, and cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied body of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: as this ſick man was healed in his body, by troubling the cleere water: Chriſt his blood ſhedding being (in iudgement of wicked men) as vnlikely to worke vs any good, as ſalt to make fruitfull, or muddy water to make a lame man whole. In this, Chriſt Ieſus our debt for ſinne is diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and vpon his croſſe is the obligation of ordinances (that was againſt vs) faſtned,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 3.18.</note> and he is the very purgation that cleanſeth, the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing eye-ſalue that giueth light,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Colloſ.</hi> 1.13. 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17.</note> and the wel-beloued ſonne of God, by whom our cries are conueied to his father, in whom he receiueth and heareth our plaints, and for vvhoſe ſake wee enioy all the bleſſednes and good things that euer we haue.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Chriſt wholy altered the nature of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions to his owne Church.</note>Now therefore in this Chriſt our alone Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. ſickneſſe to his faithfull members is as comfortable as health: affliction as ſweete as peace, aduerſitie as acceptable as proſperitie,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:7112:46"/>
death as welcome as life, the graue as a moſt ſweete perfumed chamber, for the bodies of the Saints to lie in: for they can with S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1.</note> 
               <hi>There is no condemnation to them that are in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> It makes them not feare death, but rather in Gods appointed time deſire it, in ſeeing the miſeries of this preſent life, and by a liuely faith ſoaring vp into the vnſpeakable ioyes of the life to come. And therefore they ſay with <hi>Paul: We know, that if this earthly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle of ours be diſſolued,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>we haue a building giuen of God, not made with hands; but eternall in the heauens.</hi> And Chriſt Ieſus whether wee liue or die, is vnto vs both in life and death ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage: yea, we ſeeing that while we liue,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.10. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.21.</note> we are naked in this world, we ſigh; deſiring to be clothed with our houſe, which is from heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And ſeeing while we are here iournying vpon the earth, wee are abſent from our head and husband: therefore we deſire to be diſſolued,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.23.</note> and to be with our husband &amp; Sauiour, which is beſt of all. And finally, ſeeing there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in this world, but corruption,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1.1.2.</note> alteration and vanitie, we waite, we looke, and long for the day of our refreſhing, when we may fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer lift vp our heads, meete our elder brother in the clowdes, and receiue the incorruptible crowne of glorie, laid vp in ſtore for all the Lords elect, ere euer the foundations of the world were laid.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:7112:47"/>Thus Gods children may reioyce, when the wicked ſhall howle and weepe, they ſhall bee ſatisfied as it were with marrow and fatneſſe, yea euen when they ſeeme to be full of faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: when the fat buls of Baſan, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring lions ſhall be ſent emptie away: yea they ſhall clap their handes, and lift vp their heads for ioy of that. In terror and feare wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the wicked ſhall gnaſh with their teeth, grin like a dog: and for auoyding of it (though all in vaine) they ſhall wiſh the rockes to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, the hils to couer, and the mountaines to be as a ſhelter vnto them, from the glorious preſence of him that ſitteth vpon the throne. Thus death againſt the godly hath no ſting, hell againſt the Chriſtian hath no victorie,<note place="margin">Reade <hi>Heb.</hi> 12 11. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.8.9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 34.18.19 <hi>&amp;</hi> 119.71.</note> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction is not our confuſion, as husbandmen vſe to bring dead trees and burne them in the fire: but our affliction is for our firmer &amp; fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſolation and edification: like as a good husbandman purgeth his vine, that it may bring forth more fruite.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.5.</note> Heauineſſe with the godly may endure for a night: but aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly peace &amp; ioy commeth in the morning. Seeing then that thus happily it goeth with vs all in our greateſt afflictions (if we belong vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt) I will conclude as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth his treatiſe of our immortall ſtate in the life to come: that ſeeing death once had dominion ouer vs, but is now deſtroyed; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:7112:47"/>
hurted vs, but now they profit vs; ſickneſſe affraied vs, but now comforteth vs: euen thankes and all thankes be giuen for euer to God the father,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.57.</note> who hath giue vs this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie victorie, through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now for the wicked, their ſickneſſe, ſores,<note place="margin">As for the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked it is not ſo with them.</note> griefes and vexations, are ſtill vnto them as ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends of ſinne, tokens of Gods wrath, and (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they ſpeedily repent) euen beginnings (as I ſaid before) of the flaſhings of hell fire. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie not but the godly man may haue for the outward operation, the ſame ſickneſſe, ſore,<note place="margin">
                  <p>For the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſickneſſe they may agree. <hi>Cal. in Pſal.</hi> 37.19.</p>
                  <p>A difference betweene the afflictions of the godly and vngodly. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.4</p>
               </note> griefe and trouble, that the wicked and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly haue: yet inwardly euer this difference ſhall be found: <hi>Quòd Deus ſuis in neceſſitate manum porrigens, impios deferit:</hi> God in time of his childrens neceſſities, bee they neuer ſo great, ſtill ſtretcheth out his hand for helping them, and vpholding them, leaſt they fall: but as for the wicked, it is not ſo with them: he vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly reiecteth them, forſaketh, and giueth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer vnto their owne hearts luſt.<note place="margin">Propter pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</note> 
               <hi>Flagellantur iusti propter probationem, iniusti ad perditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem:</hi> The godly are afflicted for their greater triall: but the wicked are afflicted for their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, becauſe of their great ſinnes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 9.13.14.</note> 
               <hi>For the people</hi> (ſaith <hi>Eſay) turneth not vnto him that ſmiteth them, neither doe they ſeeke the Lord of hosts. Therefore will the Lord cut off in one day from Iſrael, head and tayle, branch and ruſh.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:7112:48"/>
Pijs afflictio eſt diſciplina: qua docetur iram Domini effugere, &amp; voluntati eius obſequi:</hi> Afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the godly is for diſcipline in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, whereby they are taught to auoide the Lords wrath, by reformation of their liues, and willingly to yeeld obedience to his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements. Whereupon <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>When we are iudged,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.32.</note> 
               <hi>wee re chastened of the Lord, becauſe we ſhould not be condemned with the world. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pijs verò afflictio, eſt obduratio, qua a malo in pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius progrediuntur, ſicut Pharaoh.</hi> But vnto the wicked,<note place="margin">In euerie af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction two things to be conſidered.</note> afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is a meane of hardening their hearts, whereby they proceede from worſe to worſe. In euery affliction two things are to be conſidered: firſt, Gods iudgement: ſecondly, Gods mercie.<note place="margin">The wicked partaker of the former but neuer of the latter.</note> The wicked in their afflictions are partakers of the one, which is Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: but neuer of the other. The godly are partakers of both; iudgement for their ſinnes, mercie for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake. Hereupon ſaith <hi>Nahum:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nah.</hi> 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>Good is our God, and comfortable to his owne children in the day of trouble.</hi> And <hi>Dauid: Call vpon me in the day of trouble, and I will deliuer thee.</hi> Loe his mercie, whereof the wicked are neuer partakers. So that herein ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth againe wherein the godly are commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> partakers with the wicked in afflictions, and where they differ.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 85.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt thing that I will note out of this part and ſo end it; is this: That in the words,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:7112:48"/>
               <hi>ſinne no more,</hi> we may note that the Lord was priuie to al his former ſinnes and offences that euer before he had committed: and therefore it is, as if he ſhould ſay, I haue ſeene, noted, and obſerued all ſuch ſins, as euer before this thou haſt committed, either publikely or priuately, inwardly or outwardly, by thought, word and worke: and for the ſame haue afflicted thee, and alſo in the end deliuered thee: take heede therefore thou ſinne no more. Hence note the Lord hath Eagles eyes to ſee the corners of our hearts, and all our ſinnes neuer ſo cloſely committed: nothing ſo ſecret but it ſhall bee made manifeſt:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. Read <hi>Pſal.</hi> 138.</note> and that which is committed in corners, ſhalbe publiſhed on the houſe top. Then euer hereafter let euery man worke as in the day time, walke as in Gods preſence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue themſelues as hauing the Lorde an eye vvitneſſe, who if we doe well, in his mercie vvill accept of vs: but if wee doe euill,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.7.</note> then know ſinne ſtandeth at the doores, who will neuer ceaſe crying in the eares of the Lord for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, till ſuch time as it bee powred downe vpon the wicked in fearfull manner, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted vpon the vnbeleeuers, to their euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting deſtruction. And thus much for the ſecond part of the words of exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is, that ſinne was the cauſe of his long ſickneſſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:7112:49"/>
            <head>THE THIRD SER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MON OF THE DVTIE OF OVR DELIVERANCE.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The third Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow followeth the third part, <hi>vz.</hi> what muſt be the effect of his health, recouerie, or what muſt bee the dutie of his deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance: drawne out of the ſame wordes that the other part was, though not in the ſame ſence, <hi>Sinne no more.</hi> This is the ſubiect of the whole trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, deſcribing the dutie that this man healed muſt euer bee mindfull of, to his louing and mercifull father for his great and large deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: and in him may fitly bee gathered the dutie of all Gods children to the Lord, for ſo many liberall and louing mercies, as conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually he powreth vpon them.<note place="margin">Particulars ſhewing the mercies of God.</note> How greatly this poore man was bound to render thankes to the almightie for his deliuerance, I haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſet down in ſome particulars: as the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous diſeaſe ouer his whole body: the long continuance of it, euen moſt of his life: the little good that any likely meanes of outward medicine did for him, with ſome other moe: the conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whereof, could not but make him returne from the water with <hi>Naaman,</hi> and come to offer the rich and precious gift of his
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:7112:49"/>
whole heart to the Lord, as an acceptable ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, wherewith hee in mercie is euer well pleaſed. The like courſe if euery one of vs would take, after our great and marueilous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerances, euen with the Ruler,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.52.53.</note> whoſe ſonne Chriſt had healed, being at the point to dye, to enter into a ſerious and through ſearch,<note place="margin">This particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar courſe is meete for all of vs, the more to moue vs to thankfulnes.</note> of the very particular circumſtances, of the daunger wherein we were, and the deliuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce thereout in Gods mercie; it could not but vrge the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacie of this point wonderfull much, <hi>Sinne no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt I will by ſome examples and proofes out of the Scriptures ſhew, how from time to time the godly being deliuered out of any dangers, either ſpirituall or corporal], the Lord hath required, and they willingly haue acknowledged ſome ſpeciall dutie therefore. <hi>Moſes</hi> with the Iſraelites, hauing enioyed the great and memorable mercies of the Lord, in ouerthrowing <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and deliuering them from him, letting them goe through the red ſea as on drie land, doe preſent]y ioyne all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with hart and voyce to praiſe the Lord, <hi>Moſes</hi> beginning, and they all following in the heauenly melodie of thankſgiuing, thus: <hi>I will ſing vnto the Lord:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.1.</note> 
               <hi>for he hath triumphed gloriously: the horſe and him that rode vpon him hath he ouerthrowne in the Sea.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 4. The deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note> 
               <hi>Pharaohs charets and his hoste hath he caſt into the Sea:
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:7112:50"/>
his choſen captains alſo were drowned in the red Sea.</hi> Therfore as his dutie, he acknowledgeth &amp; ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 2. The duetie.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord is my ſtrength, and my praiſe, and he is become my ſaluation. He is my God, and I will prepare him a tabernacle. He is my fathers God, and I will exalt him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5. <hi>Ver.</hi> 27.</note>The Lord hauing giuen <hi>Deborah</hi> and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rak</hi> a triumphant victorie ouer their cruel ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie <hi>Siſera, Deborah</hi> thereupon reaſoneth of the miracle in her ſong, and reſolueth of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming a moſt excellent dutie, as thus: <hi>They that remaine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note> 
               <hi>haue dominion ouer the mightie: the Lorde hath giuen me dominion ouer the ſtrong.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>He</hi> (meaning <hi>Siſera) bowed downe at her feete he fell downe, and lay ſtill: at her feete he bowed him downe, and fell and when he had ſunke downe, he lay there dead.</hi> Therefore as our dutie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 2.3. The duetie.</note> 
               <hi>Praiſe ye the Lord for auenging of Iſrael, &amp; for the people that offered themſelues willingly.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 12.</note> 
               <hi>J will ſing vnto the Lord: I will ſing praiſes vnto the Lord our God. Vp Deborah, vp, ariſe, and ſing a ſong ariſe Darak, and loade thy captiuitie captiue, thou ſonne of Abinoam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107. The deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> rehearſing in the 107. Pſalme ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and great deliuerances: as firſt of diſperſed ſtrangers, and their miſerie, verſ. 3.4.5.6.7. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance out of captiuitie and priſon, verſ. 10.11.12.13.14. and laſtly, the deliuerance of poore toſſed ſhipmen from the dangers of the ſeas, verſ. 25.26.27.28.29.30: addeth the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:7112:50"/>
of all ſuch as are deliuered therefrom, thus:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 8.15.21.31. The duetie.</note> 
               <hi>O that men would therefore praiſe the Lord for his goodneſſe, and declare the wonders that he doth for the ſonnes of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the 105. Pſalme, <hi>Dauid</hi> from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereof, vnto the latter end thereof,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105. The deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note> is wholly occupied in expreſſing Gods miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and merciful power, in protecting Iſrael from <hi>Abrahams</hi> time (when they were but a few in number, and ſtrangers in the land) till ſuch time as by a mightie hande; and out-ſtretched arme, he brought them into the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant land of Canaan. And in the laſt verſe he noteth what vſe they muſt make of ſo many mercies, and what dutie diligently they muſt walke in, for Gods fauourable dealing with them, thus: <hi>That they might keepe his ſtatutes, and obſerue his lawes. Praiſe ye the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 45. The duetie.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Many moe proofes I might alleadge out of the word of God, for corporall deliuerances beſtowed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Church from time to time, and what muſt be the duty of ſuch deliueran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: but theſe may ſuffice for the plaine proofe of outwarde deliuerances and their duties.<note place="margin">Of ſpirituall deliuerances. The deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. <hi>Luke.</hi> 1.74. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 77. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 79.</note> Now of ſpirituall deliuerances, and their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <p>Being deliuered out of the hands of our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: knowledge of ſaluation giuen vnto vs by remiſſion of our ſins in Ieſus Chriſt: light giuen to vs that ſit in darknes, and in the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:7112:51"/>
of death, and guiding our feete into the way of peace: muſt of neceſſitie in the parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of this deliuerance, bring forth this duty: <hi>euen to ſerue the Lord without feare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 74.75. The dutie.</note> 
               <hi>in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and righteouſnes all the daies of our life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in his Epiſtle to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.12. The deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note> noteth a great deliuerance in a fewe words: <hi>The night is paſt:</hi> and being ſo, neuer forget the dutie which followeth: <hi>therefore let vs caſt away the workes of darknes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 13.14. The dutie.</note> 
               <hi>and put vpon vs the armour of light, hereafter to walke honeſtly as in the day time, not in gluttonie, and drunkennes, chambering and wantonnes, ſtrife and enuying: but put yee on the Lorde Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.20. The deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. The dutie. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 20.</note>
               <hi>Paul</hi> telleth the Corinthians of a great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance, thus: <hi>Ye are bought with a price: and therefore your dutie is to glorifie God both in your ſoules &amp; bodies: for they are the Lords.</hi> And againe, <hi>Seeing ye are ſo dearely bought, and purchaſed with ſuch a pretious pearle: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be not the ſeruants of men.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.23.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18.19. The deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note>
               <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh of a moſt comfortable deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance: <hi>Yee know that yee were not redeemed with corruptible things, as ſiluer and gold, from your vaine conuerſation: but with the pretious blood of Ieſus Chriſt, as of a lambe vndefiled and without ſpot.</hi> And therefore ſeeing the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſing of our ſaluation was a matter of ſuch difficultie: for ſiluer and gold could not doe
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:7112:51"/>
it, a matter of ſuch neceſſitie: for the diuell ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ouer vs, as a cruell tyrant: a purchaſe at ſuch a high rate, and the matter of it of ſuch a pretious valuation: for it was the blood of Chriſt, being moſt pretious, and the lambe of God vndefiled and without ſpot:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17. The dutie.</note> all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians duties therefore it is that are partakers hereof, euen hereafter to paſſe their time, and ſpend the daies of their dwelling here on earth in Gods moſt holy feare.</p>
            <p>Now out of all theſe teſtimonies and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples which haue hetherto beene allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, concerning Chriſtians duties, for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerances either ſpirituall or corporall, may further very fitly bee gathered what is the end of the grace and fauour of God towards vs, in,<note place="margin">The end of Gods mercies towards vs.</note> by, and through his ſonne Chriſt Ieſus, euen thus: <hi>Vt Deo reconciliatus peccator, ſalutis ſuae authorem, piè, ſancte<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vtuendo colat:</hi> That the ſinner being reconciled to God, muſt euer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter glorifie the author of his ſaluation, by lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a holy and vncorrupt life. Yea, <hi>Eodem verbo quo venia nobis offertur, ſimul vocamur ad poenitentiam:</hi> By that ſame powerfull word of the Lorde, whereby health, life, libertie, or forgiuenes of ſinnes is offered vnto vs: by the very ſame word is ſounded out vnto vs, <hi>Sinne no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now it followeth more throughly to ſearch into the naturall ſenſe and meaning of theſe
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:7112:52"/>
words,<note place="margin">The naturall ſenſe &amp; mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the word.</note> 
               <hi>Sinne no more:</hi> and to ſet down chiefly what is meant hereby: the which words vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by our Sauiour Chriſt to the man healed, I take it may bee thus reſolued. Whereas thou from the firſt time of thy cradle, till now, that I looked vpon thy diſtreſſed caſe, haſt been no better then a dead man, in thy ſinnes and treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Eſay.</hi> 5.18.</note> drinking ſinne like water, and drawing n ſin as it were with cart ropes, ſin raigning in thee,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.12.</note> and Satan triumphing ouer thee, by captiuating and enthralling all the powers of thy ſoule, to his owne bend and obedience, making thee come when he called, and runne when he bad thee: this ſickneſſe in thy ſoule made ſores in thy body, and thy ſenſeleſſe and ſecure conſcience brought an vniuerſal lame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to thy carkaſſe: ſo that as the parts of thy ſoule being bereaued of their powers, were no better then withered and vnprofitable bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 15 5.6</note> euen ſo the whole conſtitution of thy diſeaſed body, lay withered and dead, no part able throughly to miniſter comforts to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, till ſuch time as I viewing thy caſe, had compaſſion on thy calamities, and in my po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer healed that diſeaſe with a word, which all outward medicines could neuer doe by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual practiſe. Seeing it is ſo, the wages I wiſh is a continuall watch againſt ſinne, my fee, a feare to offend, and all the reward I require, is true, heartie, and vnfained repentance for all
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:7112:52"/>
thy ſinnes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.</note> an acceptable ſacrifice wherewith I am alwaies well pleaſed. And as before through ſinne thou waſt ſicke, through ſinne thou waſt weake, and by reaſon of thy ſinnes thou couldeſt not ſtand vpright: ſo now thy ſinnes being pardoned, thy ſickneſſe healed, and thy former ſtrength reſtored: riſe vp from ſinne, awake from ſleepe, and liue no more the life of the wicked. Thus then I gather the ſcope and drift of our Sauiour Chriſt his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to bee, to draw the man healed to true repentance, the acceptable price he muſt pay to his God for all his mercies. And the phraſe of wordes, are euen the very ſame both in ſound and ſenſe, that the firſt part of true repentance is deſcribed by vnto vs in the olde Teſtament: As in Eſay. 1.16. <hi>Wash you, make you cleane, take away the euill of your workes from before mine eyes, ceaſe to doe euill.</hi> And Pſal. 34.15. <hi>Eſchue euill.</hi> And againe, Eſay 55. verſ. 7. <hi>Let the wicked forſake his waies.</hi> And in Iere. 14. <hi>O Ieruſalem, waſh thy heart from wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes.</hi> And in Ezech. 16.61. <hi>Remember thy waies, and be aſhamed.</hi> And Iere. 4.4. <hi>Breake vp your fallow ground, circumciſe the foreskin of your hearts, and be no more ſtiffenecked.</hi> And in the new Teſtament for the ſame purpoſe are theſe words vſed: <hi>Crucifie the old Adam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Colloſſ.</hi> 3.5. Two partes of true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</note> 
               <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the earthly affections, &amp;c.</hi> For whereas there are two parts of true repentance: the firſt
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:7112:53"/>
called a killing, the ſecond a quickening; the firſt a dying, the ſecond a renewing; the firſt a forſaking, the ſecond an embracing; the firſt a caſting off, the ſecond a putting on. And to conclude, the firſt a ceaſing from ſinne, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond a continuance in care of a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, the man is here exhorted by our Sauiour Chriſt to true repentance, by killing the olde <hi>Adam,</hi> dying to his iniquities, caſting off the vnfruitfull workes of darknes, and neuer ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning as he hath done before,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.11.</note> which is the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part of true repentance. For this is the firſt degree of repentance to ſaluation, that the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner forſake his former follies, which before he hath frequented, renounce his former life wherein before hee liued, and frame his whole doing to the rule of righteouſneſſe, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were out of frame. So that I may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, where there is no forſaking, no remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, nor better framing, there is neuer brought forth any thing, but fained, hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall, and phariſaicall repentance. Hence out of all this which hath been deliuered, may it firſt be ſaid to the man healed, and in him to all in generall who haue taſted and inioyed in abundance the ſweete mercies of God, in the mediatour of the new Teſtament Chriſt Ieſus: and eſpecially to you my countrimen, who cannot deny but Gods mercies haue bin mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied vpon you in moſt ſweete manner,<note place="margin">Applie it to yourſelues.</note> euen
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:7112:53"/>
like vnto the dew of Hermon that fell vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hil of Sion, &amp; watered the dry earth that gaped for it: that for the man, he was like the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e that was throughly dunged, and manured about: and of ourſelues it may be ſaid; what could the Lord haue done more for vs his vineyard, then already he hath done, ſeating it in a fruitfull hill, hedging it, gathering out the ſtones of it, and planting it with the beſt plants, building a tower in the middeſt,<note place="margin">Looke to thy ſelf wel, ſeeing this is thy caſe.</note> and making a wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe therein? That therefore to the man Chriſt ſaid in effect: this is my laſt yeere of my dunging and manuring, either ceaſe from thy folly, and offend me no more, or elſe looke for nothing but hewing downe with the axe of my iudgements, and to bee burne vp for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. But happy man, and thrice happy, ſo hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by Chriſt in his body: for it wrought in him euer after the ſauing health of his ſoule. And to you my beloued neighbours, let me in the behalfe of our gracious God cry, that the matter and caſe on his part, going ſo with you as it doth, either now or neuer bring foorth fruites worthie amendment of life: you that haue hitherto been awake, but not with wine;<note place="margin">Our wicked and damnable courſe enforce our effectuall calling.</note> dead, when you ſeemed to liue; Atheiſts, ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, and ſtrangers from the common-wealth of Iſrael, ſtopping your eares at the voyce of the crier, ſenſeleſſe at the ſtroke of Gods ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, perſecuting thoſe that prayed for you,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:7112:54"/>
contemning thoſe that gaue you holeſome counſell: and finally, you that all your liues long hitherto haue ſported and ſolaced your ſelues with ſinne, as <hi>Sampſon</hi> with <hi>Dalilah,</hi> ſhake off your ſinne, awake from ſleepe, and ſtand vpright, open your eares, and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe your hearts, and let the Lords voyce enter into your ſoules, crying: worke as in the day, heare as from the Lord, and walk as in his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence: to whom let vs all make anſwer with a ſweete reſounding eccho thus: Thy voyce, thy call,<note place="margin">Happie are we if we heare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right.</note> thy law, thy lore, and eke thy praiſe will wee beare, obey, extoll, and magnifie all the daies of our life being here on the earth. This if we doe, then happy ſhall we be: ſtand faſt for aye, and a parcel of the Lords vineyard beloued for euer: but if we doe not, but delay the time of our repentance, as we haue done: oh alas, I muſt and will tell you what he will then doe vnto vs ſinfull, wicked, and careleſſe contemners of his graces, euen take away his hedge from vs, breake downe his wall, lay vs waſte,<note place="margin">A fearfull af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terclap.</note> and neither plant, prime, cut, nor digge vs any more: and then marke what wofull ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quell thereupon ſhall follow: we ſhall be tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den downe, eaten vp, and deſtroyed by the wilde bore out of the forreſt: and no good ſhal then grow amongſt vs, but brambles and bryers, tokens of his wrath: as in <hi>Adma</hi> and <hi>Zeboim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:7112:54"/>Againe, as this exhortation ſerueth to the man that neuer taſted of repentance before, that now without delay hee turne vnto the Lord, ceaſe from his ſinne, and bring foorth fruites worthy amendment of life: ſo likewiſe it may ſerue, and bee in place of a louing and pithie exhortation to the proteſtant,<note place="margin">It ſerueth as an exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of our countrie. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 11. Marke our happy caſe on Gods behalfe. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.</note> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor of Chriſtianitie in theſe our daies, whoſe caſe on Gods behalfe is like to <hi>Mary Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalens,</hi> out of whom went ſeuen diuels: like to <hi>Lazarus,</hi> who was raiſed from death to life, after foure daies rotting in his graue: like to the Epheſians, quickened, raiſed vp, made new, and brought to ſit in heauenly places, by the blood of Chriſt, from aliants and ſtrangers to the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-wealth of Iſrael, without hope, without God in the world: yea of forreners and ſtrangers, made citizens with the Saints, and of the houſeh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d of faith. And to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude on Gods behalfe, like to the vntoward and trewantlike ſchollers, of whom the author to the Hebrues maketh mention, who were lightened, taſted of the heauenly gift,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.3.4.5.6.7.</note> and were made partakers of the Holy-ghoſt, caſted of the good word of God, and of the power of the world to come. The profeſſors I ſay on Gods behalfe, being in as happie a caſe as <hi>Magdalen:</hi> grace offered from God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by his ſonne Chriſt, to diſpell and driue backe Satan, and diſpoſſeſſe them of many
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:7112:55"/>
diuels, as comfortable a caſe as <hi>Lazarus</hi> was in, called by the ſounding miniſterie of Gods word, out of the pit and graue of their ſinnes, where they haue not laine almoſt foure daies, as <hi>Lazarus:</hi> but by an inueterate cuſtome of ſinne, all their daies rotting therein, yet at laſt made to heare this powerfull voyce, <hi>Awake thou that ſleepeſt, and ſtand vp from the dead, &amp;c.</hi> And to conclude, of no people made a beloued people; of aliants from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth of Iſrael, made owners and heires thereof by grace; and of ſeruants by nature, made ſonnes vnto God, by adoption in Chriſt Ieſus. But theſe profeſſors of the Goſpell, ſo gratious on Gods behalfe, who hath layd out himſelfe, and his mercies wholly in his ſonne Chriſt vnto them all: yet in regard of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and the courſes of their liues, not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the fooliſh Galathians,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1.</note> who did for a time run well, but in the end obeyed not the trueth, loued their Apoſtle ſo dearely,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.15.</note> that they would haue plucked their eyes out of their heads to haue done him good: yet after a time harke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to falſe Apoſtles, they accounted him their vtter enemie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 16.</note> be;cauſe hee told them the trueth. Theſe at the firſt publiſhing of the Goſpell were very feruent, accompting it ſweete: but after ſome trials for the ſame laid vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, they fainted, adiudging themſelues vnable to vndergoe the burthen. And to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:7112:55"/>
though they begun in the ſpirite, yet <hi>Paul</hi> was afraid of them, that they would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together end in the fleſh. Yea, fitly may ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of our Chriſtians at this day, be compared with the proteſtants againſt whom <hi>Peter</hi> wrote, who promiſed vnto others libertie,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.20.</note> and yet were themſelues the ſeruants of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: who after they had eſcaped from the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thines of the world, through the knowledge of the Lord, and of the Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, were yet againe tangled therein. And to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, as I compared them to the Epheſians before, in regarde of the multitude of Gods mercies offered them: ſo now may I againe fitly reſemble them to the ſame Epheſians, but not in the ſame ſenſe as before, being now comparable with them for careleſnes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apocal.</hi> 2.4.</note> cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and luke-warmenes in Gods ſeruice. For vnto the Epheſians Angell or paſtor, <hi>Iohn</hi> the Diuine was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded to write diuers things: amongſt which, this for one, that the Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians had forſaken their firſt loue.</p>
            <p>Thus then the caſe going with vs all that profeſſe the Goſpell, ſo happily, ſo comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly on Gods behalfe, euen raiſed vp to ſit in ſpirituall places with Chriſt Ieſus: and ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly and ſo doubtfully on our own parts, amongſt many, in regarde of their ſenſuall, carnall and careleſſe cariage of themſelues, in the middeſt of a ſinfull and crooked gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration:
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:7112:56"/>
this dutie of the ſicke mans deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, laid downe and deſcribed in our text here by Chriſt, may ſerue very fitly for vs all, and be continually applied of euery one of vs, and ſtil ſounding in our eares, as though Chriſt were calling vpon, or conferring with vs, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Behold, thou art made whole, ſinne no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ye that were dead in your ſins hath Chriſt quickened:<note place="margin">Marke well ô my brethren.</note> ye that were ſtrangers from the life of God, through the ignorance that was in you, becauſe of the hardnes of your hearts, hath he illuminated and opened the eyes of your vnderſtanding, that ye may ſee and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne of things that differ one from another. Yea vnto you all that profeſſe the Goſpell let me ſpeake: Behold, beho]d, ye that were deaffe doe heare,<note place="margin">Bleſſed bee God for it.</note> ye that were lame doe goe, ye that were dumbe doe ſpeake, ye that were leprous are clenſed: and ye poore ſoules whom Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan once ouerruled, keeping you in darknes, poperie &amp; ſuperſtition, to you, to you I ſay is the Goſpell preached, the happy newes of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation ſent, and the kingdome and glorious throne of Chriſt Ieſus erected amongſt you. But me thinke I heare ſome ſay, that the man to whom theſe wordes were firſt vttered by Chriſt,<note place="margin">The ſecure reaſoning of many.</note> had cauſe and great cauſe to put in practiſe this holeſome counſell: for hee was made whole, not onely in ſoule, and the parts
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:7112:56"/>
thereof, but alſo in his body, when he neuer ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected any recouerie: but as for vs, or as for me, although the ſpirituall bleſſings wee feele and perceiue: yet for bodily healing, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing from dangers, wherein can wee finde it? O my beloued, behold further, and ye ſhall ſee what mercies the Lorde hath magnified towards you, in regard of corporall health, or bodily deliuerances.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is not vnknowne what deuiſes Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan by his miniſters,<note place="margin">An anſwer vnto it.</note> hath vſed both forren and domeſticall, for the ſubuerſion of our gratious prince, (the ſtay of our ſafetie, and the ſtaffe of our ſtrength, next vnder God) the inuaſion and poſſeſſion of our Realme by forrenners: and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all theſe, behold we are made whole, and both the deuiſer and the deuiſes brought to nought. For other deliuerances corporall, as from famine, the peſtilence, the running iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues, and the burning feuer, whereof moſt parts of our land haue taſted, I ſpare to ſpeake: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee are ſo lately made whole, or deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from them, and doe conclude my anſwere of the obiection, with <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle to the Romanes: <hi>If God ſpared not his owne ſonne, but gaue him for vs all to death: how ſhall he not with him giue vs all other things alſo need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for vs?</hi> Nay, bleſſed be God, he hath giuen vs them alreadie: ſo that now hence follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the dutie he requireth; of you Magiſtrates
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:7112:57"/>
that profeſſe to defend the Goſpell, by the ſword of your authoritie; of you paſtors that preach the Goſpell; and of all others that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly profeſſe the Goſpell in more zeale, and forwardnes for outward ſhew, then many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; to you all I ſay, take heede, looke to your ſelues, that ye receiue not the grace of God in vaine: that ye do not crie Lord, Lord in voice, and deny him in your liues; that yee bee not profeſſors, and no practiſers; hearers, but no doers. Sinne no more in your looſe liues, as you haue done, by diſpenſing with iuſtice, daubing vp the Lords wall with vntempered morter, riſing vp earely, or ſitting vp late to drinke ſtrong drinke, defiling your bodies by the vncleannes of whoredome, blaſpheming God by ſwearing, or prophaning the Sabboth of the Lord, by following your worldly buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes: for with theſe ſinnes I am afraid, many that profeſſe the Goſpell are defiled, whereby iuſtice is peruerted, the Lords building hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the godly offended, and occaſion of ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling to the weake ones thereby adminiſtred, and generally by meanes hereof, the wicked vncircumciſed Gentiles, haue taken an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of blaſpheming the glorious Goſpell of Chriſt Ieſus, as the wicked by <hi>Dauids</hi> offence in his daies. Doe not account the ſhew of this worlde ſuch a ſiluer ſhrine as you doe: doe not with one hand receiue Chriſt, &amp; with
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:7112:57"/>
the other embrace this euill world with <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas:</hi> Kiſſe not Chriſt once, and after with <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> betray him: be not ſo newfangled this day, as with the Phariſees to cry, <hi>Hoſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, welcome Chriſt,</hi> and to be altered ſoone af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with the Camelion, crying kill, and cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him. Let not ſuch vnſauorie and vnſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication come out of your mouths: as ſometime one ſhall heare euen from thoſe that brag much of the Goſpell either concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning worldly matters, or their vaine ſportes and paſtimes of this life. Doe not for a time affect &amp; loue your paſtor for his meſſage ſake, and after a while to bring itching eares, that vnles he will ſpeake <hi>ad placidum,</hi> you will perſecute him, and vnleſſe he wilbe a wether-cocke to transforme himſelfe fit for your hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors: you will account him an vnprofitable watchman: runne not too faſt for feare you faint, neither runne aſide for feare you fall in the ditch: but runne ſo as you may finiſh your courſe with ioy: lay your building vpon that corner ſtone, as you reſolue to perſeuer: beginne not in the ſpirit, and ende in the fleſh: remember from whence ye are fallen, euen from your firſt loue, and your former care: repent, and doe your firſt workes, yee that know the way of truth, walke in it, worke by it, let word and deed, profeſſion and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe be <hi>ſimul eodem, &amp; circa eadem:</hi> concurre
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:7112:58"/>
together for the aduancement of the glorious crowne and kingdome of Chriſt Ieſus. And to conclude, in the bowels of Ieſus Chriſt I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech all you my brethren by profeſſion, giue no more ſuch a ſcandale, by your lewd liues, as you haue done, neither to Iewe nor Gentile, to thoſe that are without or within the Church: take the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> herein for an example: walke more warily, that the Goſpell on your behalfe be not euill ſpoken of: &amp; finally dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloued, let your light ſo ſhine before men &amp; let your conuerſation be ſo honeſt among the Gentils, that they ſeeing your good works may glorifie God our heauenly father in the day of their viſitation. And thus much of the force of theſe words <hi>Sinne no more</hi> to all that doe profeſſe the Goſpell of Chriſt, not ſo ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely as they ought.</p>
            <p>It followeth now to ſet downe the meaſure of this dutie: <hi>Sinne no more. viz.</hi> How, and of what manner of ſtrength ſinning no more ought to be with the godly: and here we may not thinke that the drift of our Sauiour Chriſt in laying downe his dutie, is to perſuade the man healed, or in him anie one of the godly: that he expecteth in them an immunitie and freedome altogether from ſinne and the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants thereof, and that after our deliuerance from dangers, either ſpirituall or corporall, we ſhould become ſo perfect in our profeſſion of
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:7112:58"/>
Chriſtianitie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay.</hi> 64.6.7. <hi>Prou.</hi> 20.9. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.21. 1. <hi>King</hi> 8.46.</note> as that we ſhould be altogether pure from the blots and blemiſhes of any ſin whatſoeuer. For the example of the godly of all ages, recorded in the booke of God, teſtifie the contrarie: who ſtill feeling in them a rebellious nature, prone and prompt to ſinne, doe pray continually for ſtrength a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſame. And in all humiliation doe proſtrate themſelues,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.2. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 130.3. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.5.6.7.8.9.10.11.</note> before Gods tribunall ſeat, humbly crauing the Lord neuer to enter into iudgement with them for their ſins daily committed: vſing theſe or the like ſpeeches: Enter not into iudgement with thy ſeruant O Lord, for if thou doeſt, no fleſh ſhalbe iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before thee. Again, If thou ô Lord marke what is done amiſſe, oh who may abide it. The rule of praier giuen by our Sauiour Chriſt enforceth this point, teaching the godly while they liue, euer to pray, forgiue vs our debts,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.12.</note> the authoritie of the ſcriptures confirmeth the ſame in many and ſundrie other places,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.17.</note> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vs to acknowledge and confeſſe, when we haue done all that euer we can, we are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ſeruants: <hi>And that if we would,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>we haue no ſin, we deceiue our ſelues, and the truth is not in vs:</hi> ſo that hence,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1.8.</note> if any ſpirit there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, ſo fooliſh as dare affirme, that the Church and the particular members thereof ought to be a pure and ſanctified Church of it ſelfe, and in it ſelfe, from all ſtaine and corruption, either
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:7112:59"/>
in doctrine or manners,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The only per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in this life is to know our ſelues im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect.</hi> Ierom. in epiſt. Nunquam ad perfectione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingemus, niſi confecto noſtro ſtadio. Cal. in Epheſ.</note> we are taught what to anſwere, that we can neuer be partakers of that totall freedome, and finall victorie ouer ſinne, and the poiſon thereof, till that mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie be ſwallowed vp of immortalitie: and we enioy the preſence of him that ſitteth vpon the throne. The meaſure then of our ſinning no more, that the Lord requireth of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as the duetie of their deliuerance, is the verie ſame which the Apoſtle <hi>Paule</hi> vrgeth to the Rom. <hi>Let not ſinne raigne in your mortall bodies that ye ſhould obey it in the luſts therof: Neither giue ye your members as weapons of vnrighteouſnes vnto ſinne, but giue your ſelues vnto God.</hi> VVherein the Apoſtle willeth the Rom. to ſtraine and ſtriue, that (being by Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt deliuered from the bondage of ſin, and the ſlauerie of their ſpirituall Pharaoh) ſin get not the dominion ouer them againe, that it ſhould not like a mercileſſe tyrant rule ouer them againe, neither that euer their powers and ſtrengthes ſhould ſerue to Sathans becke and bend againe: but to labour continually, that ſin may die, the old <hi>Adam</hi> may be ſlaine in them, and a continuall care, and principall ſtudie to ſerue God, ſhould beare the rule, and haue the preheminence in them.<note place="margin">Calu. in Rom. Cap. <hi>6.</hi> ver. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tamet ſi pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum in nobis reſidet, tamen abſurdum eſt, vt ad exercendum ſuum regnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vigeat:</hi> Although ſinne while we liue will haue ſome reſiancie
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:7112:59"/>
with vs: yet is it verie abſurd and vnmeet that it ſhould ouerrule vs. <hi>Totis viribus extingue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do in nobis peccato,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bucer. in Rom. Cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; vitae Dei excitanda in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtere debemus:</hi> Striue we muſt with all our ſtrength, that ſinne in vs, may more and more be leſſened, and the ſpirituall life of God rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and quickned in vs, by Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. This proofe of the Apoſtle <hi>Paule,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo pregnant, for confirming this point of the meaſure of our ceaſing from ſinne, &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming obedience to the Lord, I wil (as God ſhall guide me by his holy ſpirit) inſiſt a little further in laying downe the reaſons and argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that the Apoſtle vſeth in the two afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid verſes: That ſinne in the godly ought not to rule and raigne, and carie them captiue af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their conuerſion, as it did before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let not ſinne raigne in your mortall bodies.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The firſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</note> The firſt argument he alleadgeth to proue that ſinne ought not to raigne in them, is drawne from the filthineſſe and power of ſinne: it is a moſt filthie and daungerous matter to ſuffer ſinne to rule in you, and to exerciſe power in you. But vnleſſe you withſtand ſinne with all your ſtrength, and keepe continuall watch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, he will breake in vpon you, and bind the keeper of the houſe: this part is drawn out of theſe two words, <hi>ſinne raigne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ſecond argument.</note> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond reaſon is drawne from the effect of ſinne which is death, for it is ſinne that cauſeth our
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:7112:60"/>
bodies to be mortall, as hath beene proued at large before: this the Apoſtle noteth in theſe words, <hi>mortall bodies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The third ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</note>The third argument is drawne from the compariſon of our worthineſſe in Chriſt, clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with his righteouſnes, with the filthineſſe of vnrighteouſnes. For if we giue our members vnto ſinne, we make them the weapons of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſnes, by meanes whereof iſſueth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from them but that which is vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous altogether, whereas God hath created them in Chriſt to be inſtruments of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes drawne out of theſe words: <hi>Your members weapons of vnrighteouſnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The fourth argument.</note>The fourth reaſon is drawne from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of ſinne &amp; God: <hi>viz.</hi> of eternall death and eternall life: for when as the Apoſtle had ſaid: <hi>Giue not your members to ſinne:</hi> he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexeth the contrarie and ſaith: <hi>But giue your ſelues wholly to God:</hi> And that he may expreſſe with what ſeruice and endeuour we ought to addict our ſelues to God, and his worſhip, he doth not ſay barely: <hi>Giue your members to God:</hi> as he forbiddeth them to giue them to ſinne, but hee ſaith: <hi>Exhibete vos ipſos vtique totos:</hi> Giue your whole ſelues vnto God, euen all that euer is in you.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The fift ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</note>The fift argument is drawne from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious gift of God, which is beſtowed vpon vs by Chriſt. <hi>viz.</hi> That when as through ſinne
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:7112:60"/>
we were dead, now we liue being endowed with the life of God: then why ſhould we not apply our ſelues and whole ſtrength, for the continuall enioying of it? eſpecially when as to make a relapſe into ſinne againe is to fall into euerlaſting death (without Gods great mercie in Chriſt) from eternall life, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in theſe words, as they that are aliue from the dead.</p>
            <p>The ſixt and laſt argument is drawne from the excellencie of righteouſnes:<note place="margin">The ſixt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</note> the weapons and defence whereof we make our members, when as we giue them vnto God, and dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate them vnto all holineſſe, the ſpeciall end, for which they were giuen vs of the Lord. Now by the due and carefull conſideration of all theſe arguments, the diligent and carefull Chriſtian out of this one proofe, ſhall finde himſelfe compaſſed about with many reaſons and ſound argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, all enforcing this point. After thy deliuerances beſtowed vpon thee by God, <hi>Sinne no more: Viz.</hi> ſuffer not ſinne to make thee his ſlaue no more, to make thee his carthorſe, to rule and raigne in thee, to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey his luſtes, to giue eare to his inchante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: but hauing the vncleane ſpirit driuen out of thee, entertaine him no more, being eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped from the filthineſſe of thy ſins, fall not into thy old wont and vomit of ſinne againe, but ſtriue and ſtraine to be lead forward to
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:7112:61"/>
perfection.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.24. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.24. <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.12.</note> Follow hard toward the marke: ſo run, that thou maiſt obtaine and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend that, for whoſe ſake alſo thou art com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended of Chriſt Ieſus: out of all which I may inferre this concluſion, no ſtriuing, no ouerruling, no victorie ouer our ſinnes wee haue had: moſt certainly no conuert, no true Chriſtian, no dutifull man, for his manie and great deliuerances.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Heretikes. Papiſts. Cath. Coeleſt. Donat. Perfect. <hi>See Cal. in Epheſ.</hi> 1. <hi>ver.</hi> 4</note>Now becauſe the arguments of the Papiſts Catherans, Caeleſtins, Donatiſts, and vnpure Perfectiſts, for prouing and confirming an abſolute obedience to the law of God, &amp; a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall puritie from ſinne, amongeſt the godly in this life, ſeeme to the reader at the firſt view to carrie ſome weight, I will a little more ſtand vpon the confutation of their obiections &amp; the right ſenſe and meaning of thoſe teſtimonies of ſcripture, which they falſely peruert to their owne deſtruction, &amp; the endangering of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie.<note place="margin">Ierom. aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Pelag. ad Cteſiphon.</note> And firſt let me ſet downe what <hi>Ierome</hi> his iudgement is of them in theſe wordes: <hi>What greater raſhneſſe can there be, then for a man to chalenge to himſelfe, not onely to be like, but to be all one with God: which poyſon hath iſſued from the impure fountaine of the Philoſophers: and eſpecially Pythagoras and Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no, who affirmed that thoſe which the Graecians call <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; we paſſions: as griefe, hope, fear, ioy. &amp;c. may be puld out of mans minds, &amp; that no
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:7112:61"/>
ſtring, or roote of vices at all, may be remaining in men, through the exerciſe of vertue: which is to take man out of man, and for a man being in the body to be without the body.</hi> Thus farre <hi>Ierome.</hi> And the ſame man a little after in the ſame treatiſe, ſaith very excellently thus: <hi>He that alwaies forgetteth things paſt, and longeth for things to come, ſheweth that he is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with, neither that there is any perfection in this preſent world.</hi> The aduerſaries, being by the examples of the diuers falles of the faithfull in all ages: their humble confeſſions concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their imperfections: and the manifolde teſtimonies of the word to this end, ſo hampe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1. Obiection.</hi> See Cal. lib. <hi>2.</hi> inſtit. cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> that they are grauelled and can go no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: haue no refuge, but are conſtrained to flye to the almightie power of God: leauing what man can do of himſelfe, reaſoning what is Gods power in man.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> We anſwere and doe not denie, but God can perfectly regenerate vs in this life, if hee will: but why hee doth it not, he hath many cauſes: among the reſt note theſe. Firſt, that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> wee may diligently conſider the power of ſin, how great it is, and what effect it hath in man, which we ſee cannot bee deſtroyed in vs, but by little and little, &amp; that by the ſpeciall grace of the ſpirit: and therefore we are ſo much the more to be afraid of it. Secondly, that when <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> to this life we finde no end or ſtay of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:7112:62"/>
betweene the fleſh and the ſpirit, we may ſo much the more long for that bleſſed life, wherein wee ſhall appeare before God, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly regenerate and holy: whereas if God ſhould out of hand renew, and totally ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie vs, the dignitie ſhould not bee of ſo great accompt with vs: but now, by little and little bringing the ſame to paſſe in vs, the perfection thereof is ſo much the more deare vnto vs. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Laſtly, for this cauſe God doth not perfectly here regenerate vs, to the end that his power may bee made perfect in our weakneſſe: and when wee are ſaued by meere grace, and not of workes, he that reioyceth may reioyce on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>2</label> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.15.</note>The Scripture (ſay they) attributeth perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the godly, ſaying: <hi>As many of vs as are perfect, let vs be thus minded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> When <hi>Paul</hi> reckeneth himſelfe amongſt the perfect, he ſpeaketh not of ſuch a perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of faith in vs,<note place="margin">Cal. in Phil. <hi>3.15.</hi>
               </note> as the Perfectiſts do imagine: but hee ſpeaketh there of the perfection of knowledge, in reſpect of the only foundation of our ſaluation Ieſus Chriſt: when caſting away confidence in all things, vvee reioyce in the onely righteouſneſſe of Chriſt Ieſus: and ſetting all other things aſide, to attaine to the fellowſhip of his ſufferings, which may bring vs to the bleſſed reſurrection. So that this proofe, which they vſe as a daunt to driue vs
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:7112:62"/>
from the trueth, may wee vſe as a ſword to pearce them thorow, who withſtand ſo plaine a trueth. Secondly, it is true by compariſon,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>vz.</hi> If you compare perſons with perſons, that there is more vertue and knowledge to bee found in one man, then in another: ſo the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles well inſtructed in Chriſt, were called perfect, in reſpect of them who being too much ſet vpon ceremonies of the Law, were pulled aſunder from the body it ſelfe. So <hi>Noah</hi> for his life, is ſaid to haue been a iuſt and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect man in his generation.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>3</label> They alleadge further, that ſo earneſtly to maintaine this imperfection, is to make Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſlothfull: which otherwiſe by preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perfection, would be pricked forward to the attaining thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> I anſwere: that the knowledge of a mans owne imperfection in this life, doth rather ſtirre the godly forward, to endeuour to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to perfection, and euery day to goe ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly forward in the courſe of their calling: &amp; to ſtriue with the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.11.</note> if by any meanes they may attaine to the reſurrection of the dead. Which obiection being thus anſwered, appeareth manifeſtly how wicked, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly againſt this ſound and holeſome doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the vnperfect obedience of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in this life, is that Canon of the Triden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Councell, Can. 18. ſeſſ. 6. enacting thus:
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:7112:63"/>
               <hi>If any man ſay, that the commaundements of God are impoſſible to be kept, euen of a man iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified and vnder grace, let him be accurſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here for the ſummary concluſion of this point, I cannot omit the teſtimonies of two ancient learned fathers, concerning the premiſſes:<note place="margin">Auguſt. contra duas epiſt. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lag. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Augustine</hi> ſaying thus: <hi>With what preſumption doe they openly gainſay the Lords prayer, wherein all the members of Chriſt doe cry with a true heart, and daily voyce, forgiue vs our debts?</hi> And a moſt excellent ſaying is that of <hi>Cyprian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cypr. epiſt. de mortal.</note> who ſaith: <hi>We haue a combat with couetouſnes, with wrath, with ambition: we haue a daily and troubleſome wraſtling with the corruption of the fleſh, and with the entiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the world. If couetouſnes be vanquiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, luſt riſeth vp: if luſt be ſuppreſſed, ambition commeth in place: if ambition bee contemned, wrath galleth, pride puffeth vp, drunkennes allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, wickedneſſe cutteth off friendſhip: and yet it pleaſeth a man to ſtay long amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g theſe ſnares of Satan: whereas wee ought rather to wiſh to make haſte vnto Chriſt, where we may bee freed from them all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt point that I haue thought good to note out of theſe wordes, <hi>Sinne no more,</hi> is the priuate and particular vſe and application, that euery one partaker of any deliuerance, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpirituall or corporall from the Lorde, muſt make to his own ſoule, concerning ſuch
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:7112:63"/>
dutie as the Lord requireth of him, which is this: That the wordes and power of them, ſhould euer ſound vnto his owne ſoule, as a ſummon, to bid him awake, ſtand vp, and walke no more in the courſe and waies of his former wickednes, as thus: O thou man, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer thou bee, who haſt taſted moſt abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly the ſweete mercies of thy God, eſcaped many dreadfull dangers, paſſed many perils, the Lord ſtill preſeruing thee, and ſhadowing thee vnder the wings of his mercie, till they were all ouerpaſt: looke now to thy ſelfe, how thou walkeſt hereafter: not ſo looſely, negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently and diſobediently, as thou haſt done before: ſinne no more in vnthankfulnes, as thou haſt done: ſinne no more in contemning Gods long, louing, and gratious viſitation: ſinne no more in prophaning the Lords day: ſinne no more by thy drunkennes, adulterie, Atheiſme, contempt of Gods word, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny moe ſinnes, wherein thou haſt been found faultie: let Gods iudgements, ſhaken at thee as a ſword for thy ſinnes, terrifie thee: let the ſame now remoued allure thee, euer hereafter to walke, and worke, as in the preſence of the Almightie. And thus may euery priuate ſoule, now ſaued from daungers, ſound out the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arme of his continuall dutie, in manner and forme aforeſaid: euer labouring and ſtriuing,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:7112:64"/>
that the Lords preſeruation from imminent dangers, may bring foorth and breede in vs reformation of life, and mortification of ſinne raigning in vs.</p>
            <p>And thus much for the dutie of the man deliuered: wherein hath bin ſhewed at large, the dutie of vs all for Gods many and miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous mercies, whereof we haue of late moſt abundantly taſted: and which whole point is the ſubiect of this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie treatiſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="sermon">
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:7112:64"/>
            <head>THE FOVRTH SER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MON OF THE DVTIE OF our deliuerance: drawne out of the laſt words of the text: <hi>Leaſt a worſe thing come vnto thee.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow followeth the fourth and laſt part of this treatiſe,<note place="margin">The ſumme of the words.</note> which is the louing and friendly ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueat of our Sauiour Chriſt to the man healed: forewarning him of the danger that would enſue, if he did not preſently put in practiſe the dutie of his deliuerance, contained in theſe wordes of the text: <hi>Leaſt a worſe thing come vnto thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In theſe words vttered by our Sauiour Chriſt to the man healed, is deſcribed the danger this man was in, if he ſinned againe, euen a worſe thing to fall vpon him. The Lord in his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſicknes had dealt with him like a ſonne: but if he continue obſtinate, and offend again, he will plague him like a wayward ſeruant. He had viſited him with a long ſickneſſe, to purge him, that he might be a profitable pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: but if after this purging of the Lorde, hee ſtill became vnprofitable, hee will the next time plucke him vp by the rootes, and caſt him into
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:7112:65"/>
the fire. In his former ſickneſſe God ſhewed his mercifull power, and powerfull mercie in healing him, when he had no hope to be hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: but if he fall and offend againe, the Lord will ſhew his iuſt power, and powerfull iuſtice in condemning him.<note place="margin">The danger of a relapſe into ſinne againe, after God hath deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vs out of dangers. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.6.7.</note> The man ſtood there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in a dangerous caſe, better he had neuer been healed, then ſinne againe: better neuer to haue receiued the ſweete raine and dew of Gods bleſſings, then after the receipt of them, to bring forth nothing but bryers and bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles: for ſo hee is nie to curſing. Out of all which I gather this doctrine, <hi>vz:</hi> That when for ſinne God hath inflicted ſickneſſe, ſores, and griefe vpon any, and afterward he in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie hath healed the diſeaſe, by remitting the ſinne, and the partie ſo healed doth fall after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward into his accuſtomed manner of ſinning againe: that ſame partie, whoſoeuer he or ſhe be, is in great daunger that God will inflict a greater plague vpon him, then euer he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. For proofe hereof, reade Leuit. 26. from the 14.<note place="margin">Reade <hi>Leui.</hi> 26. from verſ. 14. to the end of the chap. and <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.</note> verſe to the end of the chapter, where the ſeruant of God <hi>Moſes</hi> ſetteth downe, that for the peoples diſobedience, and contempt of his lawes, God will bring a conſumption, and a burning ague: but if they will not for theſe things repent, he will puniſh them ſeuen times more: if they will not then repent, hee will plague them ſeuen times worſe then that.
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:7112:65"/>
The Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> rebuketh <hi>Iſraell,</hi> that though ſhe was in captiuitie, yet was ſhe not humbled thereby to forſake her ſinnes:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos.</hi> 5. <hi>verſ.</hi> 10.11.12.</note> but rather worſe and worſe in contemning his Prophet in oppreſſing the poore, in peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting iudgement, by taking bribes: the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet propheſieth &amp; telleth them that a worſe thing ſhall come, then euer befell them hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto: for whereas they ſeemed to crye for the day of the Lord, he telleth them the day of vengeance ſhall fall vpon them in ſtead of the other. Yea one iudgement ſhall follow after another.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>As if a man did flie from a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and a beare, and did meet him, or went into the houſe and leaned his hand on the wall, and a ſerpent bit him:</hi> Gods iudgementes ſhall be readie to ſeaze vpon him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 24.</note> what way ſoeuer he turne him. Wiſedome telleth the wicked, that becauſe ſhe hath ſtretched out her hand, to correct diuerſe of her rebellious ſonnes, and yet they continued wicked,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 28.29.30.</note> and would none of her correction, loe the next time ſhe will ſtretch forth her hand, but not as before: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe ſtretched and ſpread abroad both her armes of mercie, clocking her diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren vnto her: <hi>As the hen gathereth her chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens vnder her wings:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 23.37.</note> But her ſecond ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhalbe as an Eagle prepared for his pray, to bring vpon them ſodaine deſolation and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction like a whitewind. <hi>Eſay</hi> ſpeaking in
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:7112:66"/>
the perſon of the Lord to his rebellious <hi>Iſraell</hi> ſaith:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſy.</hi> 65.12.</note> 
               <hi>I ſhall number you to the ſword, and all you ſhall bow downe to the ſlaughter: becauſe I cried and you did not anſwere, I ſpake and ye did not heare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierem.</hi> 2.30.</note> 
               <hi>but did euill in my ſight. Ieremie</hi> complaineth, <hi>that although they were ſmitten and corrected, yet all was in vaine:</hi> And howe fearefull a thing it is, after God hath giuen vs health or deliuerance out of dangers, to offend him againe by our looſe life, appeareth by <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his fearefull ende,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 13.28. <hi>Luke.</hi> 17.17.</note> and by that ſharpe cenſure Chriſt gaue of the nine leapers by him cleanſed, and yet remained vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4.</note> And if it be ſo dangerous to ſinne againe after the recouerie of the health of the bodie; much and more dangerous it is for thoſe to fall againe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.26. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.45.</note> whom God hath enlightned with the ſight of their ſinnes, and knowledge of the truth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.6.</note> for they entertaine other ſpirites worſe than the former, they crucifie againe the ſonne of God, and therefore better had it beene for ſuch neuer to haue knowne the way of truth, then after they haue knowne it, to prophane it,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.13.</note> by their lewd and wicked practiſes, leaſt a worſe thing come vnto thee.</p>
            <p>This word (leaſt) doth not here ſignifie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vncertainty, as being a thing proceeding from man,<note place="margin">The right ſenſe of the word (leaſt) in this place.</note> whoſe promiſſes or threatings are vncertaine: but it ſignifieth a thing moſt aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly, that will come to paſſe, as being a iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:7112:66"/>
proceeding from the father of light,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.18. Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are not to be dallied withall.</note> with whom is no variablenes not ſhadow of turning. We may not dally with the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of the Lord here, as <hi>Euah</hi> did with the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement in Paradiſe: who whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord had abſolutely threatned death to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſſoon as euer they ſhould tranſgreſſe his commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; <hi>Euah</hi> by the ſubtiltie of the ſerpent is brought to make a peraduenture of that which God abſolutely ſet downe, and ſaith:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>Of the fruite of the tree in the middeſt of the garden, God hath ſaid, ye ſhall not eate leaſt ye die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may be, ſome now a daies may ſooth vp Gods iudgements and threatnings,<note place="margin">The ſpeech of a careleſſe Atheiſt.</note> and ſooth themſelues in their ſinnes and ſay, tuſh, to ſin is not ſo great a daunger as it is taken to be, for we ſee them that moſt offended, floriſh faire, and ſtand as wel as the beſt: and beſides, his iudgements are but threatned with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture, or perhaps take heed ye catiffes, and thriſe blinded men of the world. For this word (leaſt) ſignifieth thus much: That hee aduiſeth them to beware, for if he doe not,<note place="margin">A bone for ſuch to gnawe vpon.</note> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly a worſe thing will come vpon him. And that Gods iudgements threatned againſt the wicked, are without any peraduenture, as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a God not vncertain what to do; marke what <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaketh in the perſon of the Lord: <hi>If I whet my glittering ſword, and my hand take hold on iudgement,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.41.42</note> 
               <hi>I will exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:7112:67"/>
vengeance on mine enemies, and will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them that hate me: I will make my ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes drunke with blood, and my ſword ſhall eat fleſh:</hi> And <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith: <hi>God ſhall wound the hairie ſcalpe of ſuch an one as goeth on ſtill in his wickedneſſe.</hi> And the authour to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes,</hi> hauing perſwaded to holineſſe of life, addeth the daunger,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.29.</note> and ſaith: <hi>For our God is euen a conſuming fire:</hi> Again the ſame author ſheweth the danger all ſuch are in, as by their continuance in ſinne (after they haue receiued the knowledge of the truth) do crucifie againe the ſonne of God, addeth as a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion theſe words: <hi>It is a fearefull thing to fall into the hands of the liuing God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.31.</note> To conclude therfore this point: Gods iudgements being threatned againſt the wicked for ſinne, they are ineui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table without alteration: vnleſſe they preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put in practiſe the holſome counſell of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">What will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Gods iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> aduiſing them to enter into a ſerious and ſound adiudging of themſelues, and ſo they ſhould eſcape the great and fearefull iudgementes of the Lord,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.31.32</note> which was partly begunne alreadie in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion amongeſt them, and partly was readie to be inflicted vpon them. It muſt be an eye to ſee Gods iudgement, a heart to feele Gods iudgement, a conſcience to condemne, and all concurring together, to proſtrate, throwe downe, and truly to humble the ſinfull man,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:7112:67"/>
vnder Gods mightie hand, crying with the prodigal ſonne: <hi>O father I haue ſinned againſt heauen and againſt thee: and am not worthie to be called thy ſonne:</hi> I ſay it muſt be, all theſe wrought moſt ſoundly by the worke of Gods ſpirit in the ſinner that muſt be as a ſtoppe to Gods iudgements, and a ſtay of his anger manifeſted. <hi>Leaſt a worſe thing come vnto thee, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe words may be the ſpeech of a maſter to his ſeruant thus: I haue taken thee napping twiſe or thriſe, nay often, and haue louingly admoniſhed thee of it, but if thou plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt the like again thou ſhalt ſmart for all: or of a ſchoolmaiſter to his ſcholler, whoſe waggiſh trickes and great negligence he hath often pardoned: but now threatneth the next time ſhall pay for all. Euen ſo God from time to time ſeemed to winke at the ſins of this man,<note place="margin">What the Lord long for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth.</note> yea euen at the ſinnes of vs all, and like a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſchoolemaſter beares a while with our of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences: but either now ceaſe from ſinne, learne to doe well, and be a good ſcholler in Chriſtes ſchoole, or elſe looke thy lord and maſter, the Lord <hi>Iehouah</hi> will take an account for all, and in the ende pay thee home.<note place="margin">(Leaſt) importeth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie.</note> (Leaſt) this word (leaſt) vſually in the ſcriptures importeth great neceſſitie of the matter in hand to be put in ſpeedie execution, as in <hi>Ieremie:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierm.</hi> 4.4.</note> 
               <hi>Breake vp your fallow ground, ſow no more among the thornes, be circumciſed to the Lord, and be no
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:7112:68"/>
more ſtifnecked, leaſt my wrath breake forth and burne like a fire &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.12.</note> And the Pſalmiſt: <hi>Kiſſe the ſonne leaſt he be angrie, and ſo ye periſh ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainely, if his wrath be kindled, yea but a little &amp;c.</hi> And that neceſſarie admonition of our Sauiour Chriſt to his Diſciples <hi>Watch and pray leaſt ye enter into temptation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 22.40.46 <hi>Math</hi> 26.36. <hi>Mar.</hi> 14.32.</note> And laſt of all, that earneſt caueat of the author to the <hi>Hebr.</hi> to all the godly Iewes, for perſeuerance in the profeſſion of the Goſpell, and practiſe of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly daies meete for the meaſure of the grace of God they had receiued, ſaith thus: <hi>Take heed brethren (leaſt) at any time there be in any of you an euill heart and vnfaithfull to depart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the liuing God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.12 <hi>&amp; verſ.</hi> 13.</note> Out of all theſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forenamed phraſes may be gathered the vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent neceſſitie that was impoſed vpon this man healed, preſently to put in vre the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall dutie of his deliuerance,<note place="margin">The vrgent neceſſitie of performing dutie to the Lord.</note> and inſinuateth alſo vnto euery one of vs, or rather as a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall cry ſoundeth in our eares. O ye negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, coole, careleſſe, diſobedient, and ſcorne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full people in the North parts of England, who deſeruing Gods wrath for your manifold ſins are yet now in the multitude of his mercies,<note place="margin">An Alarme to the North parts of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note> freed &amp; deliuered from the effect of his wrath, <hi>ſinne no more,</hi> leaſt if you againe tempt and prouoke the liuing Lord to anger, he call you to recken and giue an account for your ſelues,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.9.</note> &amp; ſo ye ſhall neuer be able to anſwere one of a
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:7112:68"/>
thouſand. Further in that our Sauiour Chriſt heere admoniſheth the man healed of his daily danger, if euer after hee, doe not cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie the olde <hi>Adam</hi> with the luſtes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of:<note place="margin">God euer war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth before he plagueth.</note> we note the louing care &amp; mercy of God, not to bring deſtruction vpon any, before he hath both largly &amp; louingly forewarned them of the danger, yea he deſireth not the death of a ſinner, but rather that he conuert and liue according to the rule of the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 18.23.</note> the Lord is not ſlack as ſome men count ſlacknes, but is patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t towards vs, would haue no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to periſh,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9.</note> but would haue all men come to repentance, and all are inuited to the mariage of the Kings ſonne. To conclude therefore this point,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. No cauſe to cenſure the Lord of hard dealing in iudgement.</note> we learne heere that all excuſe or cenſuring the Lord of hard dealing in iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is remoued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wicked, ſeing all of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo the intollerable burthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his wrath are offred moſt abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to drinke of his loue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[A worſe thing.]</hi> For the conſideration of the meaſure and greatnes in ſome ſort of this puniſhment, which heere is threatned the man if he offend againe,<note place="margin">View in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer.</note> I wiſh thee diligent &amp; wiſe reader, to g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue a glaunce backe to the viewe of his former ſickneſſe, and certainly that will giue thee ſome probable demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtration of the meaſure of his puniſhment againe.<note place="margin">Cal. in Ioh. Cap. <hi>5.</hi> verſ. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> It is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry likely that his correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was laid vpon him in his youth and the verie time, which by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:7112:69"/>
yeeldeth pleaſure to the bodie, was alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether painefull:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 5. <hi>verſ.</hi> 5.</note> continuing with him, the ſpace of 38. yeares, all that while no vſe of his bodie, to miniſter any comfort. Whereupon I may ſay with <hi>Clauin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cal. cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od.</note> to euery man that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidereth hereon: <hi>Quàm grauis fuerit tot an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum poena, reputa:</hi> Waigh well with thy ſelfe how painefull was the continuance of ſuch a grieuous paine, for the aggrauating whereof, this one thing did not a little worke, that when this poore ſoule ſo long had beene ſoaked and bathed in his affliction full 38 yeares, he grew to be forlorne, forſaken, and helpeleſſe altogether in reſpect of any man: continually many diſeaſed, by helpe of others brought to the poole, and ſo healed, and yet he a diſtreſſed ſoule, pitied of none, relieued by none, expecting ſtil, ſome would cary him, but all in vaine, crying for comfort, but comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſtill: ſo that with <hi>Iob</hi> we may well ſay, that he ſeemed to be euen as a butte, or marke that God had ſet to ſhoote at, and to pierce through with the arrowes of his anger, and that to mans iudgement hardly a more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortleſſe ſorrow could be laid vpon him, and yet lo at laſt healed by him,<note place="margin">Chriſt healeth when it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be paſt healing.</note> who euer healeth, when all meanes of healing ſeemed to fayle: this man I ſay, is now by Chriſt admoniſhed to looke to the dyet of his ſoule, that he do not ſurfet with ſinne againe, leaſt a ſorer plague
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:7112:69"/>
befall, both bodie and ſoule, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> befell him before: a ſorer will you ſay how can that be? for in his former viſitation he was comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe,<note place="margin">A glance to his former griefe.</note> helpeleſſe, and hopeleſſe in regard of man: oh, how then can a worſe thing come vnto him, I wiſh all men aſwell thoſe that haue felt great and grieuous troubles either in bodie or ſoule, or both themſelues, as alſo thoſe that haue beene eye witneſſes, or eare witneſſes of their neighbours, or countries great afflictions:<note place="margin">Beware of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods iudgement.</note> to beware of ſuch like com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints as there: or aggrauating their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſo greatly, as though God had not in ſtore a greater for them, if they offend againe, and to make all that ſhall reade this, more cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect in this point, I will ſet downe the excellent ſaying of the afore-recited author <hi>Caluin</hi> touching this one point:<note place="margin">Caluin cap. eod.</note> 
               <hi>Non dubiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, quin ſibi horrendas ſaepè, &amp; prodig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> crucia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, miſeri homines, improbis ſuis quaerimonijs accerſunt, dum nigant mala ſua augeri poſſe.</hi> VVithout all queſtion, wicked men do heape vpon their owne heads, many great and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full iudgements,<note place="margin">Complaining againſt God haſtneth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</note> while after a complaining manner they cry out and ſay, their griefes are ſo great, and puniſhments ſo intollerable, that God can lay no greater vpon them: let this euer be a warning vnto vs all,<note place="margin">Patience in paines is profitable.</note> patiently to abide, &amp; willingly to wait for our deliuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce out of dangers, and being deliuered, carefully
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:7112:70"/>
to put in practiſe the dutie that we owe for our deliuerance: leaſt if we doe not, a worſe thing come vnto vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A worſe thing</hi>] Two waies eſpecially Chriſt here threatneth to bring a woreſe puniſhment vpon him then before, if hee offend againe. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, though the former puniſhment for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance was long, for paines extreame, for remedie almoſt hopeleſſe: yet is the Lord of power to inflict, and here threatneth that hee will inflict a greater and more grieuous pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, in all circumſtances then before: out of which learne this doctrine following: namely,<note place="margin">Caluine.</note> 
               <hi>Nullas eſſe tam atroces &amp; ſaeuas poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas, quibus non aliquid addere Dominus poſſit, quoties viſum fuerit.</hi> There are no puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſo great laid vpon the wicked, which the Lord <hi>Iehouah</hi> is not of power to aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate and make greater, whenſoeuer the ſame ſhall ſeeme good vnto him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, if the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> healed by Chriſt, offend and ſinne againe as before, a worſe thing ſhall befall him, in regard of the Lords protection. For though in the former his griefe was great, and his ſicknes of long continuance: yet from the beginning thereof, till the perfect healing of the ſame, the Lord euer aſſiſted him by his power, prepared him by patience and though of the one hand the poore man ſemed to bee forlorne, yet with the other hand the Lord ſtill
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:7112:70"/>
vpheld him, as faithfull in his promiſes, laying no more vpon him, but as he gaue him ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth to beare, and in the midſt thereof gaue him a comfortable iſſue thereout. But loe, the next time that the Lord commeth agaianſt him, he will not onely by his infinit power, lay vpon him a ſorer plague: but that alſo which is more fearfull, he will withdraw from him his louing protection: which bleſſed protection, did in his former ſickneſſe euer vphold him from pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing. In his former viſitation he dealt like a father,<note place="margin">Compariſon.</note> whoſe tender affection and loue to his childe, euer ouercommeth his anger: but his next viſitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (as I ſaid before) ſhalbe in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, giuing him ouer to his owne ſtrength, and in the midſt of his agonie, leauing him to ſhift for himſelfe. Which, oh alas, when that commeth to paſſe, hee ſhall neuer bee able to ſhelter himſelfe from Satans tyranny, nor ſaue him, as he was before ſaued, from deaths do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion. Hereafter let all mouthes be ſtopped, from murmuring againſt their ſorrowes: or ſaying, they are ſo great that God can make them no greater: ſeeing two waies haue been told you, how the ſame may be effected.<note place="margin">1 By greater plagues.</note> The firſt by his great power, which is without bound or limitation. The ſecond,<note place="margin">2 By ſpirituall deſertion, and by withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his former protection.</note> which more fearfull is, by ſpirituall deſertion, giuing them ouer to their owne ſtrength, and by withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from them his gratious and fatherly prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:7112:71"/>
in the time of their fearfull affliction.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The vſe.</note>Then let all in generall, and particularly all of vs my countrimen, make this particular vſe, and application hereout, to the benefit of our owne ſoules, euen throughly to examine and ſearch,<note place="margin">Search the particulars of your late viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, both by dearth and the peſtilence.</note> with what ſickneſſe, ſore, trouble, or danger, we haue been afflicted: in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, meaſure, and how long: and after this, that if extreame was our affliction, great our danger, and our caſe vtterly remediles, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſole ſaluation and deliuerance of him, who is vnto his owne Church all in all: ſurely then to determine for a moſt certaine trueth, that hereafter, unles our Lord &amp; maiſter finde vs more carefull ſchollers, in learning of his will, and more obedient ſonnes in doing his commandements: as ſure as we breathe, ſo to looke, that ere it be long, a heauier lode ſhalbe laid vpon vs, which we ſhall hardly disburthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs off. If before this, yea euen of late, the Lord hath beaten vs blacke and pale, by his ſeuere puniſhments of dearth and peſtilence: and yet being now healed thereof preſently forget our puniſhments, and God, that inflicted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon vs:<note place="margin">Though we forget God in our dutie, yet he will not forget our ſins</note> tremble and feare, for certainly then God will not forget our ſinnes: but if they hale him on to come againſt vs yet againe, take heede that with his third whip he ſcourge vs not, till blood run down from top to toe: when there ſhall be nothing heard, but a fearfull noiſe and
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:7112:71"/>
lamentation, alas, alas: in which diſtreſſe, (which is moſt fearfull) the wicked careleſſe contemners of his mercies, ſhall then ſeeke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him earely and late for helpe. But I make a queſtion whether they ſhall finde him or no: the ſhall call vpon him, but I am afraid hee will anſwere in thunder: and the reaſon doth Wiſedome tell;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 1.28.29.</note> becauſe they hated know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and did not chuſe the feare of the Lord. The cauſe doth <hi>Ieremy</hi> tell: like diſobedient children,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierem.</hi> 2.30.</note> they did not humble themſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Lord, when they were corrected. And ſurely, if a worſe thing,<note place="margin">What is the cauſe if our countrie be plagued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</note> a worſe plague come vpon our North-parts of this land againe, it is becauſe (as diuers to their griefe, haue both ſeene and heard) that many of you, great townes, great congregations, priuate families and perſons, after your deliuerances, healings, and reſtoring to your former liberty haue not with <hi>Moſes</hi> and with <hi>Deborah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.2. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5.2.</note> aſſembled your ſelues together, and lift vp your voyces in praiſe to the Lord, and a faithfull promiſe to become euer after carefull in his ſeruice: which thing you ought to haue done.<note place="margin">Much abuſe in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces &amp; townes after their late fearfull viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> But ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your meetings haue bin, and are, to ſhake hands with your former ſins, and to bid them welcome againe amongſt you: hauing for a time been taken from you, by reaſon of your affliction. Your ſongs haue not been to praiſe God, but rather (as I haue heard) in place ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:7112:72"/>
prophane Enterludes:<note place="margin">Piping and dancing. Lords of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, with many moe vnlawfull ſports. <hi>Eſay</hi> 49.13.</note> and generally your proteſtations, not one to crie to another, and all ioyntly to ſound together, ſaying: <hi>Reioyce O heauens, be ioyfull O earth, burſt foorth into praiſe O mountaines: for God hath comforted vs his ſinfull people, and hath had mercie on vs his late afflicted ones.</hi> Neither (I am afraid) haue you been carefull to ſay with <hi>Moſes: The Lord is our ſtrength and praiſe, and he is become our ſaluation: he is our God, and wee will prepare him a tabernacle: he is our fathers God, and we will exalt him.</hi> And to conclude, whereas many of you (my beloued countri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) haue been depriued of the enioying of one anothers fellowſhip,<note place="margin">Our meeting againe, after a long ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid abuſed.</note> in the time of your affliction: which now (bleſſed be the name of God) is reſtored to free libertie of fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſocietie one with another: I ſay, I am afraid, that your meetings together, after a long and lamentable ſeparation, hath not bin to prouoke vnto loue, and to good works, and to exhort one another daily,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.13.</note> while it is called to day: but rather in ſtead of this, the drunkard to aſſociate himſelfe with his drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken companions, the whoremonger to ſeeke for his harlot, the vainglorious man for his flatterers, the carnall man for his confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, the vſurer for his creditors, one wicked man with another, and ſo to renew that wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked bond and league of their ſinne: at all
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:7112:72"/>
which you ought to haue taken your laſt farewell, neuer to haue communicated any more with ſuch vnfruitfull works of darknes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shall come vnto thee.</hi>] Out of this place we may gather this excellent point: namely, that as the godly bringing forth the pleaſant fruits of righteouſnes in their liues,<note place="margin">Note well the godly goe ſtill forward till they come to heauen: but the wicked ſtil backward till they go down to hell.</note> haue ſtill more &amp; more the ſweete mercies of God multiplied vpon them, till they enioy them in their fulnes in the kingdom of glorie. Euen ſo the wicked, that after Gods graces powred downe vpon them, doe ſtill notwithſtanding bring foorth nothing, but the weedes and brambles of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, haue Gods iudgements ſtill more and more increaſed againſt them, till at the length they preſſe them downe to hell. Againe, I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hence this doctrine,<note place="margin">Thanke our vnthankfulnes if moe plagues come.</note> that if euill come vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euill, and puniſhment vpon puniſhment: we may iuſtly impute it to our owne obſtinacie, and wilfull rebellion.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, let this doctrine be the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, both of this point, and this part of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: <hi>Si nil ferulis proficiat erga nos Deus, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus leniter nos tanquam teneros ac delicatos fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lios, humaniſſimus pater caſtigat, noua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; quaſi alienam perſonam induere cogitur:</hi> If God, by his whipping of vs, profit vs nothing, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall, like a moſt kinde father he correcteth our contumacie and diſobedience: hee is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to take vpon him another habit, and to
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:7112:73"/>
manifeſt himſelfe in another manner,<note place="margin">If mercie will not moue, iudgement will throw downe.</note> change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mercie into iudgement. And therefore let vs euer learne the end of Gods fatherly corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to bee our daily reformation, and more increaſing in the gifts and graces of the holie ſpirit: euermore remembring the danger that will enſue, if daily we doe it not, and the ſharp cenſure we ſhall vndergoe if we forget it: euen this, that the Almightie <hi>Iehouah</hi> will, <hi>quaſi a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trocioribus malleis,</hi> with the heauy and inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable beetles of his iudgements, preſſe downe, &amp; vtterly bring to deſolation all thoſe, <hi>quibus mediocris poena nil profuit,</hi> that is, whoſe hearts were not mollified, and their liues re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed with the Lordes former ſweete and comfortable affliction.<note place="margin">The conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> Which (my beloued) that the former may euer take place in vs, and ſo eſcape, that the latter be neuer laid vpon vs, the Lord for his infinit mercies ſake grant vs, euen for his ſonne Chriſts ſake, who by his blood ſhedding hath ſo dearely ranſomed his Church: and vnto whom with the Father, and the holy Spirit, be all glorie, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, praiſe, and dominion for euermore. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:7112:73"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
